<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Phlebotomiographia or, a treatise of phlebotomy. Demonstrating the necessity of it in diseases; the time for elections. And likewise of the use and application of cupping-glasses, and leeches. Whereupon is added a brief and most methodicall tract of the crisis. Written originally in French, by Da de Plumis Campi chirurgion. And now faithfully rendred into English, by E.W. well-wisher to physick and chirurgery.</title>
            <author>Planis Campy, David de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 113 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2376A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1929_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209992</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868835</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868835</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121191</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90743)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121191)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 239:E1929[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Phlebotomiographia or, a treatise of phlebotomy. Demonstrating the necessity of it in diseases; the time for elections. And likewise of the use and application of cupping-glasses, and leeches. Whereupon is added a brief and most methodicall tract of the crisis. Written originally in French, by Da de Plumis Campi chirurgion. And now faithfully rendred into English, by E.W. well-wisher to physick and chirurgery.</title>
                  <author>Planis Campy, David de.</author>
                  <author>E. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[42], 176, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Streater, for John Place, at Furnisalls-Inne Gate; and William Place, at Grayes-Inne Gate, next Holburn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title is in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Septem:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Phlebotomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR, A TREATISE OF <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> Demonſtrating the Neceſſity of it in diſeaſes; the time for Elections. And likewiſe of the uſe and application of <hi>Cupp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſſes,</hi> and <hi>Leeches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon is added a brief and moſt Methodicall tract of the <hi>Criſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written Originally in <hi>French,</hi> by <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Plumis Campi Chirurgion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now faithfully rendred into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> by <hi>E. W.</hi> Well-wiſher to Phyſick and Chirurgery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Streater,</hi> for <hi>John Place, Furnifalls-Inne</hi> Gate; and <hi>William Place,</hi> at <hi>Grayes-Inne</hi> Gate, next <hi>Holburn.</hi> 1658.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:3"/>
            <head>To the moſt High and Puiſſant Princeſs, <hi>Mary De Medici</hi> Queen, Mother to the King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe cauſe which hath induced me to conſecrate upon the Altar of your exquiſite me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits this little Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb facs="tcp:121191:4"/>
(compoſed for the ruine of ſo manie <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> of our Age, who moſt commonly are the cauſe of the loſse of ſo manie perſons of all ages, qualities, &amp; ſexes, by reaſon of their undue Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Operation, viz. <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi>)
<pb facs="tcp:121191:4"/>
is, the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of ſo manie excellent and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly royal Vertues, ſhine and dart forth their ſplendor in you, which are more to be admired, than known; more to be known, then imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and more to be imitated, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualized, And which have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:121191:5"/>
birth; and being from the exquiſite perfections of your Divine wit, the Fame whereof, ſerves as a ſubject matter, for the moſt fine Wits to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend; and for an example of well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to the moſt magnanimous ſouls. Your fair actions, are as ſo many glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
<pb facs="tcp:121191:5"/>
Stars, which imbelliſh and illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Heaven of our <hi>Fraunce. Fraunce,</hi> who may from hence-forth, glorie, for having bin delivered from the devouring Gorge of a storm of miſeries, by the ſage providence of a Queen; yea, the moſt wiſe of Queens
<pb facs="tcp:121191:6"/>
that ever governed it. A Queen, with how great honours loaded? with what reſpects honoured? with how manie Triumphs cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? and with how manie Laurels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned? As manie humane mouthes, ſo manie Trophies to your Grandure; as manie hearts, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:121191:6"/>
manie Temples e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to your Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; as manie ſouls, ſo manie Vowes and ſacrifices to be imo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated upon your Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars. In brief, Your Vertues are ſuch, that I ſhall not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture to handle, raſhlie, the praiſes of them, becauſe I cannot arive there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but in admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:121191:7"/>
nor recount them worthilie but in ſilence. This ayr is too clear for the flight of my dull Plume; wherefore by the example of the Swallows, which preſage Rain, I will content my ſelf to couch to the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the Earth, to beſeech You (Madam) on the
<pb facs="tcp:121191:7"/>
behalf of our Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgerie, that you will be pleaſed to dart forth the Rays of your ſweet fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour upon this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſcantling of its Operations. For whatſoever appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion I have had of the greatneſs of Your Merits, and the weakneſs of my judgement; it hath
<pb facs="tcp:121191:8"/>
not bin able to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me from offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it up unto You for a Teſtimonie, rather of my good will to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, then for anie thing that is in it, vvorthie to ſee the Light under your Royal Authoritie, and Divine Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. If it have the favour to be vvell
<pb facs="tcp:121191:8"/>
accepted, I doubt not, but being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected by the Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Your <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva,</hi> it vvill eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beat back all the aſſaults of envie, &amp; be looked upon by all, vvith a favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Eye. And for my part, I ſhall therein take ſo great contentment, that my deſires
<pb facs="tcp:121191:9"/>
ſhal be more ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie redoubled to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear; and be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knovvledged all the reſt of my life,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               <signed>Your Majeſties, Moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt affectionate Subject and Servant, <hi>Campi Chyrurgion.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:9"/>
            <head>To the Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Reader.</head>
            <p>BAd Masters do occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the loſſe of credit to good Mysteries, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paragement to good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. The eſteem, or the ſtighting of Arts and Sciences doth depend, upon the ability or inſufficiency of thoſe who handle them; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they are well or ill pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar, without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring further into the knowledge of their cauſe, (as ſeverall perſons who will not permit themſelves to be
<pb facs="tcp:121191:10"/>
reprehended (although they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake exceedingly) in an art which they practice, with abundance of more preſumption then knowledge) do adjudge unto them (upon the firſt veiw) either good or bad reputation; ſo that ſuch actions as are commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, and thoſe that are reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full are, (by the Vulgar popularity) meaſured by the ſame rule, and weighted in the ſame ballance, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any manner of diſtinction, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that moſt commonly Vertue gives place to vice, Wiſdome to ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and Experience to incapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
            <q>
               <l>So by <hi>Capricious</hi> ignorance we praiſe</l>
               <l>Vice more then vittue and do ſeem moſt glad</l>
               <l>All at a venture to beſtow the Bayes</l>
               <l>On ignorance her ſelf, in ſurplis clad.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121191:10"/>And they will take the name of Philoſopher, formerly ſo reverend and ſo much reſpected among the Greeks, that from the time of <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras,</hi> It was cauſed to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, Wiſdom. Notwithſtanding, it is certain, that this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Philoſopher, ſignifies nothing more, nor leſſe, but A lover of wiſdome. And yet there is not a man in theſe dayes ſo ſhallow brained, ſo inconſiderable a perſon, nor ſo great a Lord, but would be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angry, yea would be inraged and take exceptions in good earneſt, if one ſhould take him for any other but [A perſon deſirous of knowledge] which to expreſſe in one word is (A Philoſopher.) A title wherewith Emperour <hi>Antoninus</hi> himſelf was well pleaſed, to be honoured. Let us conſider what courſe that title hath paſſed for ſome years past, how it was ordinarily taken; And after what faſhion it is made uſe of, now.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121191:11"/>It is the common Complement, and the little joviall Epithite which one doth uſually give, promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly at the firſt meeting a perſon, though he have the Countenance of one that hath ſlept rather then watched over his books. If one meet with a man that doth not well know the Court Carveate, nor how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute in a quarrell according to the modern faſhion, who diſcourſes with Ergees framed upon all occaſions, upon the foot of a Fly, (thereby ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf as indiſcreet in familiar common entertainment, as averſe to civill Actions,) preſently they give him the Style of Philoſopher by head and ſhoulders. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the true Philoſophy, if we may herein beleeve <hi>Ulpian,</hi> the <hi>Civilian,</hi> conſiſts in management of affaires, in the converſation and conſervation of humane ſociety, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment in matters of Law, in Court affaires, and in all the points
<pb facs="tcp:121191:11"/>
of honour; ſo that a Philoſopher, and a perſon of honour or States-man, to ſpeak properly with <hi>Ulpian,</hi> (who was ſuch an one) is one and the ſame thing. What then is it that hath imbaſed it, and brought it ſo low from ſo high a degree? Who hath ſtript and diſrobed it of all its auntient honours and prorogatives, making it ſo to ſerve as a Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-stock? but the impudent ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of a crew of Miſhappen diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed Pedants, whoſe geſture and diſcourſe ſtincks ſtrongly of the Muſtineſſe of the School, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have paſſed over a bridge amongſt a croud of Aſſes, without leaving their pack-ſaddle behind them, do preſently conjecture them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves able to hold Port with the great Horſes. Which fate, or worſe (the more the pitty) is alſo fallen upon the title Phyſitian. For I pray, what is now become of the auntient ſplendor of the Science of Phyſick? What is
<pb facs="tcp:121191:12"/>
become of its Glory and Ornament, and the inclination and well wiſhing of Auntient Princes and Potentates thereunto. Who did not think it below them to learn and exerciſe this divine Science, (by good right called Divine, in regard it receives that Elogie from the very mouth of God): But did treat it with great Liberality to confirme its dignity, and maintain its authority.</p>
            <p>(The Science of Phyſick, I ſay) which the auntient Hebrews did hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our as being come from Heaven for conſervation of health, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing of life. And it is testified by the holy writ, that the Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Phyſicians are made, inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and recommended by God, as in <hi>38. Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> Honour the Phyſician with the honour that belongs unto him, and for the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion that thou haſt for him, for the Lord hath Created him: Do not withhold from him the reward of his
<pb facs="tcp:121191:12"/>
pains, to the end, that he may ſuccor &amp; aſſiſt thee in thy neceſſity: he ſhall receive rewards from Kings and the knowledge of the Chirurgical Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, ſhall cauſe him to exalt his head, and render him admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble among Princes; As for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples concerning the Liberality of Salaries and Preſents, wherewith the Auntient Kings, Princes, and Emperours have been pleaſed to honour Phyſicians; <hi>Pliny</hi> relates that the <hi>Caeſars</hi> did allow unto the moſt famous Phyſitians, who practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Phyſick at <hi>Rome,</hi> two hundred and fifty Seſterces yearly, which (according to the Common Accompt) comes to about ſix thouſand two hundred and fifty Crowns, although the other profeſſours had but a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. <hi>Thadeus</hi> the Florentine received of every Prince that he ſerved, fifty Crownes <hi>per diem.</hi> And he having cured Pope <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> of a ſtrange diſeaſe, he had
<pb facs="tcp:121191:13"/>
allowed him <hi>100</hi> Crownes <hi>per di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em.</hi> And (as <hi>Volateran</hi> reports) a reward alſo of a thouſand Crownes. The Emperour <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> gave to <hi>Anthony Muſa</hi> (who had helpt him in a great ſickneſſe) a Gold ring inriched with a ſtone of a great price, and not content with this, he honoured him with the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of Knight of his own order. And not onely he, but alſo all thoſe who exerciſed that profeſſion, were (out of reſpect to him) honoured with the ſame Title. <hi>Darius,</hi> the <hi>Monarch</hi> of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> had <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mades</hi> (a Phyſitian) in ſo great eſteem, by whoſe aſſiſtance he had been freed from a tedious diſeaſe, that, (as <hi>Herodotus</hi> reports) he gave him two great Chaines of Gold of great value. And the <hi>Queen</hi> his wife gave him for a preſent two Bottles made of Maſſy Gold. Let us leave the Auntients and their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, to ſpeak of <hi>James Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:121191:13"/>
a moſt Learned and excellent French Phyſitian, who had as a Sallery from King <hi>Lewis</hi> the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, ten thouſand Crowns <hi>per menſem:</hi> from hence we may col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect in what esteem the Chirurgicall Phyſitians have been in all times, maintained in all Liberty and free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, exempt from all Charges, Subſidies, Tributes, Talleys, and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſts. Behold in what dignity the Phyſician and Phyſick, was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and yet notwithſtanding we ſee in this unhappy age wherein we live, (where vice marches in the ſame Rank as Virtue) it is ſo changed, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, &amp; altered that it ſeems to be now no more then an Idol or Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſm, its Countenance vailed its Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit deſtroyed, its Honour degraded, its ſtrength abated and weakned, and its reputation withered; in ſhort, it is fallen from that moſt high ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of glory, whereunto our prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had raiſed and advanced it:
<pb facs="tcp:121191:14"/>
it is (I ſay) profaned and trampled under foot by a Crew of ignorant Impoyſoners, Impoſtors, Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks Quack-ſalvers, Men of evil converſation, and Cawterized conſciences, who (like new <hi>Eſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapians</hi> deſcended from the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens) bragg impudently, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe audaciouſly the curing of all <hi>Maladies:</hi> of whom the ignorant popularity do ordinarily make more Accompt, and do give more credit to the exterior apperance of a gallant port &amp; flaunting behavior, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the vain glory of ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Apparell; than to Learning and Experience. Yea certainly, for if there be any Mountebanke, Quack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalver, or couſening drug-ſeller, ſome crackt brain fellow of an extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant wit, who giving the Carreer to his fancies ſhall mount up to a thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and make ſome ſtrange kind of Compoſitions; or elſe, if he carry
<pb facs="tcp:121191:14"/>
a Gold ring upon his finger, and his Moustaches well mounted, a well compoſed demure Countenance, and uſing theſe words often in his mouth, (to wit) Blood, Humors, Spirits, Tumours, Wounds, Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, Fractures, Diſlocation, <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates, Galen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Behold this is the man, who is reputed of every one, the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Chirurgicall Phyſitian of the whole earth. Soft, ſoft, my Maſters, not ſo quick; for you may he deceiv'd: for it is not the habit that makes the Monke. Words and deeds have a great difference. Ask theſe Mountebanks, firſt if they have the knowledge of <hi>Geographie,</hi> of the <hi>Mathematiques,</hi> of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, of Muſick, <hi>Geometry, Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, Arithmetick, Rhetorike,</hi> of <hi>Hiſtory, Poeſy,</hi> and <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy:</hi> In ſhort, in one word, he must
<pb facs="tcp:121191:15"/>
be an <hi>Encyclopaedian</hi> for he that, in one word, would call a man a perfect Phyſitian muſt call him ſo: for to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agin a Phyſitian to be ſeparated from the knowledg of his above mentioned Companions, were to ſuppoſe him ignorant, mute, and dead. Again, demand if they have the knowledge of all things that fly in the Ayr, of all things which ſwim in the water, of all Vegetables, of all things which have ſenſe or life upon the Earth; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally of all which the Univerſal Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth incloſe in her bowels, either of <hi>Water, Mettals, Minerals, Salts, Juices, Sulphurs.</hi> Beſides, if he hath entred into himſelf, there to obſerve his own ſtructure, to dive into his own bones, to number his Muſcels, to follow his veines, particularize his Arteries, ſearch out the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talages, or admire his <hi>Nerves, Tendons, Ligaments, Films,</hi> &amp;c. If they have done all this,
<pb facs="tcp:121191:15"/>
and if a ſolid Judgement, be the ſoul of their experience; in truth then you may careſſe them with im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities or privilidges, acknowledge them with applauſe; or elſe you are to blame.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſome Hypocondri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack perſon, will contradict me and ſay, that it is not fit for a Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to preſcribe rules to Phyſitians. In good time! neither do I do it to the Learned Chirurgicall Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, (for thoſe we honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect as our Maſters); but I ſpeak to a Crew of (I know not what ſort of) Medicasters, viz. without ſhame or wit, without foreheads. Oh what a number is there of them! So that now one may take up that pretty ſentence of an Auntient mans; [That the ignorance of ſome and the incredulity of others are the reaſons, why ſo many Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgicall Phyſitians are altogether
<pb facs="tcp:121191:16"/>
ignorant of the <hi>Maladies,</hi> which they hold for incurable], which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are curable, as the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy,</hi> the <hi>Dropſy, Apoplexie, Palſy,</hi> Contraction of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>falling-ſickneſſe, Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-feaver, Hectique feaver, Hand-gout, Foot-goot, Hipp-gout,</hi> and <hi>Sciatica,</hi> and ſeverall other <hi>Maladies</hi> which are hard of digestion for them. But it may be ſome one, (who doth not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand me) will be amazed to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve me to put the Chirurgion in the Rank of Phyſitians; yet I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you I do it by good reaſon, for I do not value a man who doth onely vapour, but him that ſaith and doth too. Oh miſerable age! wherein men beleeve that a Chirurgion knows nothing but how to apply Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſſes to let blood, and to ſpread a Plaiſter, and it may be 'tis true too, Alas too true, to my great
<pb facs="tcp:121191:16"/>
grief; but it is not ſuch that I mean. For the art of Phyſick and Chirurgery, is not acquired by mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, as ſome ſhameleſſe perſons have cauſed themſelves to be called Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chirurgions by that means.</p>
            <p>Oh times, <hi>O tempora! O mores,</hi> Oh manners! To this purpoſe hath one well ſaid.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Tis Gold that makes the Idiot and the Sot</l>
               <l>To be call'd wiſe and prudent and what not:</l>
               <l>And which is more, (men dote ſo on their wo)</l>
               <l>They'r well contented that it ſhould be ſo:</l>
               <l>For is it not a miſery to ſee</l>
               <l>Men of mean parts rais'd to ſuch high degree,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:121191:17"/>As to converſe in Lives, ſo uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troull'd</l>
               <l>Not for their wit or Learning but their Gold.</l>
            </q>
            <p>It coſts them ſometimes two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren Crownes at a time, a ſilke Coate, Embroydered beds, feaſts, and Banquets to friends and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and other good conſiderations, to palliate their admittance.</p>
            <p>Oh good God! what a faſhion this is to make Market of mens lives? It was better conſulting with the ſucceſſours of <hi>Cain,</hi> to indure a Plague: for then ſome, one <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> or <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> would be found to reſiſt and ſtop it. But in this caſe it ſo falls out, that thoſe who bring in the abuſes and ſupport them, will take no heed to reſiſt or overcome them. By good reaſon
<pb facs="tcp:121191:17"/>
then ſay I that the skill of Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery is not attained to by money or ſucceſſion, nor by reading onely, but by a long and painfull Laborious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry &amp; ſearch. Wherefore I do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire that there are ſuch abundance of Chirurgions who do beleeve that, which [french Authours] <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauld</hi> and <hi>Anceline</hi> have determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as an Indiſſolvable Law, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadging that ſuch an Authour hath done ſo and ſo; and that becauſe it is a cuſtome, that therefore they may do ſo too. Take notice here, my friend, that Cuſtome will not ſerve to demonſtrate the Art. And one cannot call that an art which cannot truly be demonſtrated by ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. But they will neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve this, nor take the paines to re-illuſtrate this famous Chirurgery, which hath been formerly in as great honour, as it is now in neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. Yea, one may well be aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed
<pb facs="tcp:121191:18"/>
that ſo noble a ſcience ſhould be ſo degraded from its priſtine repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that having been Antient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the favourite of Kings, and the imployment and occupation of great Perſonages; It is now abject and proſtitute to the der<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion of the most inferiour of City and Country.</p>
            <p>What is there, I pray, more famous admirable or divine, then this holy Profeſſion and yet you ſee how it is ſlieghted of every one? And (which is moſt deſtestable) by thoſe very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who are grown rich and fatned thereby, for if one propoſe unto them ſome moſt neceſſary rule, you ſhall have them immediately give the Title of Emperique by the head and ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, even to ſuch as (being friends to nature) would conſcientiouſly raiſe them from their weakneſſe: for tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there is no profeſſion wherein one ought to be more cautious of erring, then in ours of Chirurgery; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb facs="tcp:121191:18"/>
of its ſubject, which is a Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Body, a beame of divinity; and yet notwithſtanding ſome take the leſſe heed to it, and blame the good deſigne of others, and like Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſops Cock ſleight the precious Stone, and ſcatch and ſcape into the Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill. Is it not a ſhamefull thing to ſleight things that are good and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary &amp; to run to I know not what ill-grounded practiſe, which is more Empericall then rationall? I ſhall leave the judgment hereof to thoſe who, stript of all Paſſions, do know the errours which are thereby com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted; particularly to thoſe who practiſe Chirurgery, for if they erre in the leaſt operation, by much ſtronger reaſon muſt they needs erre in the greater and moſt difficult; ſo I ſay, if upon all occaſions they are at a ſtand in obſervations concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> they muſt needs be ſo by much ſtronger reaſon, in
<pb facs="tcp:121191:19"/>
matters of greater Speculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Object.</label> But, will ſome one ſay, Do you think it an eaſie thing to know the motions of the Starrs, and to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Numerous motions of the Starry Spheares, to comprehend the Directions, Declinations, and Retrogradations of the Planets, for ſo ſmall an operation as that of <hi>Phlebotomy?</hi> Beſides, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (ſay they) that theſe Chymeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call obſervations, are ſo unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that moſt commonly they pay their Scrutators, with events no leſſe distant from their expectation then the ſubject of their Science is from the Earth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:19"/>
            <p>
               <label>Anſw.</label> To which I anſwer. That truly I finde it most eaſie, in regard my Art obliges me, and my reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines me to it; but by how much, Sciences do ſeem to be difficult and arduous, they are by ſo much the more ſubjected to Calumnies and Cenſures; becauſe the ignorant, and blinde witted (ſeeing no further then the noſe-end of their ſimplicity) do ſleight all things that are diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to their underſtanding. And as for that which concerns the ſmall benefit of this Science: Stay here a little, you fanatique wits, you ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Muſes, inſenſible do-nothings, you mercenary Pipers; open the eyes of your underſtandings, be not like unto the Numean Lyon,
<pb facs="tcp:121191:20"/>
(kill'd by <hi>Hercules</hi>) which fed in the Forreſt of ignorance, making a Generall destruction of all that which was good, and conſerving that which was bad. Confeſſe inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly the excellence and worth of this Science, which diſcovers the wonderfull effects of the ordinary mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the heavenly bodies. For ſince that thoſe who lop wood &amp; dig in the earth (conſidering firſt the Poſition of Heaven) are not ignorant that many miſhaps do depend thereupon, as worm-eating and corruptions, and the like; by much more ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought we to obſerve the Starrs, for operation upon ſo noble a ſubject as a Humane Body. Which alſo was well underſtood by thoſe who do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibite the provoking of the Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrue in Women or Maids in all the four Quadratures of the Moon; not being ignorant of the power, which the Starrs have over our
<pb facs="tcp:121191:20"/>
bodies. I pray let us ask the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethliaque</hi> Aſtrologers, if when <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> do enter into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, they do not cauſe the Plague; alleadging as a reaſon, that the ſaid Planets do endeavour by all meanes to deſtroy man, whoſe radicall humour conſiſts onely in heate and moiſture, and their nature and faculty depends onely upon dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and coldneſſe. But while I ſpend paper in this diſcourſe, Me thinks I here a noiſe or buzzing of <hi>Hornets,</hi> who love nothing but dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty infectious places, I mean their own wills, who conducted by their ignorance, allwayes turn about the pot, (as one may call it) of their old doctrine; (I ſay) me thinks I perceive theſe to ſcoff at my pen, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving I treat of an operation which hath been ſo learnedly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced before our time, by ſome of the moſt ſublime perſonages which antiquity hath produced.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121191:21"/>To this I anſwer, that (although one would thinke one could ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more upon this ſubject, there having been ſeverall Volumes of it) yet notwithſtanding they are not performed with that method where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I treat of <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> in this place; not following the old opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe that would be nothing but ſinging the ſame ſong again; but diſcovering the fault which peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple daily fall into, in this ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant operation, I deſcribe a means ſo to behave ones ſelf, that one ſhall very ſeldome fall into irrepairable faults. Wherein I do aſſure my ſelf, loving Reader, that, if putting off all Paſſions, thou doſt come with a favourable eye to look on theſe Lines, (which proceeding from an honeſt Leaſure, do run the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of Cenſure) thou wilt confeſſe that it is not without great conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that I have put hand to pen,
<pb facs="tcp:121191:21"/>
to a Treatiſe of this matter. Not that I have been provoked thereunto by any vain-glory, but poſſeſſed with a good deſire to ſerve the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique.</hi> And truly I ſhould have beleeved I had faild of my duty, if having received ſomething peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar from the Liberall hand of the Almighty, I ſhould not have diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted it to the lovers of true Learning. To the end that all their and my workes, might be to the honour and glory of God, for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification and health of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and to the ſalvation of our ſouls. To which God, Father, Son, and Spirit, be rendred all honour, and glory, for ever, Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="docket_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:22"/>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:121191:22"/>A Treatiſe of Phlebotomy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:23"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121191:23"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF <hi>Phlebotomy.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> What Phlebotomy is. Its property, and of that which is to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved particularly for the good per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance thereof.</head>
               <p>MAny Philoſophers both Graecians, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and Barbarians after they had dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121191:24"/>
contemplated all ſorts of Animals, &amp; curiouſly ſought out their manner of living and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd their Condition and Nature with ours have writ that amongſt all Creatures breathing and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving upon the Earth;</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Man is more miſerable then al Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals and the reaſons therefore.</head>
                  <p>There is not any more Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable than Man by reaſon of his unſatiable deſire and diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Appetite: for continually he is hunting after new food, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found any according to his taſte, he devoureth them after ſuch a faſhion that I exceedingly admire that the bellyes of many are not already rotten and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by that exceſſe of drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and debauchery which they do commit. I am amazed in thinking of it. And what doth there proceed from it? except
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121191:24"/>
abundance of Rheums; Catharrs, and infinite other kindes of diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which do nothing but adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate change and corrupt, this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of our generation, The treaſure of life, the ſeat of the Naturall heate, the matter or ſubſtance of the ſeed, and of the Milke of the Duggs or Papps, that is to ſay, the Blood: which is ſo well diſperſed and mingled through all the parts of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, that there is not any one of thoſe parts which doth not receive its nouriſhment from it; and there is not any good thing in us which is not maintained and ſupported by It. It is the Mother of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits which does impregnate the ſeat of the faculties, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſtrength of the whole Body, which does foment and entertain its primitive moiſture; It is ſo repleniſhed with ſpirits, that the conſervation thereof is
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121191:25"/>
the cauſe of our life; inſomuch that ſome have eſteemed that it was the proper ſeat and habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Life, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our unruly wills accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with our (more then unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable) Debaucheries are cauſes that this continuance of our lives is almoſt wholly extinguiſhed.</p>
                  <p>One ſhall ſee nothing elſe in the Countryes but Doctors and Doctereſſes for the renewing of this ſcource of our lives; ſo many bloodings made improperly, that I wonder that inſtead of helping their Patients, they do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The diligence of the Learned Chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urgion praiſed.</head>
                  <p>Not that I would here blame the diligence of the Learned &amp; skilful Phyſitian and Chirurgian, who as friends to nature do endeavour with all their might to preſerve
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121191:25"/>
her in her health or integrity. And that by purging and cleanſing, or evacuation; which laſt is not to be done but by inciſion of a Veine. This is called <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> word Compounded of the Greek words <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which ſignifies a Veine and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that is to ſay, diviſion of whole parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The derivation of the word <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Behold therefore why in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular this word is taken for making inciſion of a Vein by which evacuation is made of blood and other humors contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with it: <hi>Galen.</hi> 13. <hi>Method. Ch.</hi> 6. You muſt take notice that there are ſeverall ſorts of blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; As of a Veine, of an Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Scarrifications and others: we will ſpeak eſpecially as to <hi>Phlebotomy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:121191:26"/>
                  <head>For what cauſes one ſhould open a Vein.</head>
                  <p>We make bloodings for ſix principall cauſes, The firſt. To Evacuate. Secondly, To divert turn back or make Revulſion. Thirdly, To Attract. Fourthly, To Change. Fifthly, To preſerve. And ſixthly to alleviate; which is according as all thoſe who have treated of this matter have defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it. But let us content our ſelves with theſe two Cauſes, (to wit) <hi>Plethorall</hi> and <hi>Chachochy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall:</hi> the one conſiſts in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but too great quantity of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, &amp; the other in the evil qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How far <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> doth extend its ſelf.</head>
                  <p>But the benefit of <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> doth not extend it ſelf only to the evacuation of the fulneſs, (which ought to be made according to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121191:26"/>
the kinde or difference of it) but alſo to divert, and to drain which are the three ſorts of eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation. It ſerves alſo for great and extream paines principally when they proceed from Tenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, inſomuch that all the learned Phyſitians and Chirurgions do hold that blooding, is a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent &amp; aſſured remedy, if the rules requiſite thereunto, be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in well obſerved: yea more ready and ſecure then Laxative Phyſick, which being taken works imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and forceth its operation, it not being in our power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> more ſafe then purg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Phyſick.</head>
                  <p>But <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> (the Reines of the Conduct whereof we hold) doth nothing but what ſeems good unto us, foraſmuch as we do ſtopp it and draw it forth, when we pleaſe. And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121191:27"/>
in truth, among all Chirurgicall operations, blooding holds the firſt Ranke, becauſe it is the Common remedy of diſeaſes which proceed from <hi>Plethore,</hi> and <hi>Cacochymie,</hi> as we have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; both which are the Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent cauſes of diſeaſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What <hi>Plethore</hi> and <hi>Cacochymy</hi> is.</head>
                  <p>Let us then define what <hi>Pletho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> and <hi>Cacochymie</hi> is, and then we will appropriate unto them Revulſion and Derivation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Plethore</hi> is nothing elſe then a repletion of all the humors equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly increaſed, or elſe of the blood onely.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cacochymie</hi> is a repletion of Choller Melancholy, or Phlegme. <hi>Plenitude</hi> hath two kindes the one <hi>Ad vires,</hi> and the other <hi>Ad vaſa;</hi> there is another added unto them called, <hi>Supra vires.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt, (to wit) <hi>Ad vires,</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121191:27"/>
Although that the blood be not exceſſive neither in quantity nor in quality, yet it may oppreſſe the weak powers notwithſtanding; the other (to wit) <hi>Ad vaſa</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſeth the Naturall Symmetry or proportion; But although the veſſells ſeem to burſt by reaſon of the abundance of blood, if it doth not ſuffocate the powers, but it happens that the ſtrength is debilitated thereby; This then ſhall be <hi>(plenitudo ſupra vires),</hi> But it muſt be taken notice, that <hi>Cacochymie</hi> is threefold, Chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, Melancholick and Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique. Enough of this: for he that would ſee more therein let him reade, <hi>Lafframboiſiere</hi> in his <hi>[Loix de Medicine.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us now return to Revulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Derivation where we find there is great difference between the one and th'other, foraſmuch
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121191:28"/>
as the Revulſion is to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on the Contrary part accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Galen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Galen</hi> in the <hi>5.</hi> of his Meth. Ch. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>If the right Noſtril bleed, you muſt apply a Cupping-glaſs upon the Region of the Liver; but if both do bleed, you muſt apply two; th'one upon the right Hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre or flanck and the other upon the left: and if the diſtemper be ſtrong, one muſt breathe the vein under the elbow. If the mouth and the throat be diſtempered, open the Cephalique, and it is Revulſion, and if one draw blood from the veines under the tongue, it is Derivation; In like manner, if the hinder part of the head ake, you muſt make Revulſion by the vein of the arme, then Derivation by the vein of the forehead; alſo Revulſion and Derivation muſt be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121191:28"/>
made on the ſame ſide, (if it may be); as, if there be a Phlegmon in the Liver, you muſt breathe the Baſilique or Mediane of the right Arme; If in the ſpleen, on the left; If in the kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes, the Bladder, or privities, you muſt open the vein of the ham or Ankles. If in the right Leg, on the Right Arme; <hi>Gal. in his</hi> 13. <hi>meth. Ch.</hi> 11. <hi>and Aph.</hi> 36. d. 6. If in one Arme, on the other, and ſo of the reſt, (if it maybe) as I ſaid before; foraſmuch as if there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth a Phlegmon in the Liver, and that the Right Arme ſhould be hurt, one cannot nor ought not to take any blood from it, but you ought to take it from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arme, or from the Ankle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:121191:29"/>
                     <hi>Oribas l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ch.</hi> 22. Note that they Lance the Arteries, eſpecially thoſe of the Temples, to evacuate the hot windy humors which flow into the eyes and cauſe tedious paines of the head, vertigoes or ſwimmings of the head, which are principally cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by hot things and windy, and the Arteryes behind the eares are for the ſame effect; <hi>Gal.</hi> 13. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho. Ch.</hi> 22. One never lanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Great Arteries, as thoſe of the Armes and other places; As well, becauſe of the too great diſſipation of the vitall ſpirits, as becauſe there can be no agglutination or knitting made there, by reaſon of their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall moving, we will ſpeak more largly hereof, hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:121191:29"/>
                  <head>Obſervations concerning blooding.</head>
                  <p>It is time now to know who are they who ought to be blooded, and thoſe who ought not ſo to be; Thoſe who can eaſily bear ſuch lancing &amp; to whom it can do no hurt, are thoſe who have a ſtrong conſtitution, the veins bigg, full, &amp; large, who are neither lean nor waſted, who have their colour good and ruddy, their fleſh firme hard and ſolid: thoſe who are of a contrary diſpoſition cannot bear it healthfully; neither muſt one blood Children, before the age of fourteen; nor old men after threeſcore and ten; unleſſe in caſe of great and extream neceſſity; and conſidering this, That with the blood ſlides forth part of the life, which you muſt alwayes do prudently, (meaſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the greatneſſe of the diſeaſe with the power of the Patient's ſtrength) to the end that one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121191:30"/>
may eaſily judge of the matter or ſubſtance, and likewiſe of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuation; but you ought not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider of the forces or vertue at preſent, but to know for the future if they will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſupport the length and continuation of the diſeaſe: alſo you muſt obſerve, if thoſe whom you blood have been accuſtomed to be lanced; For thoſe who have not been accuſtomed to it, do not undergo it eaſily, Inſomuch that Cuſtome muſt be conſidered in all manner of evacuation eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as to that of blood. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over all thoſe who have weak ſtomacks, or who are wrought on and oppreſt by the Dyarrhe or looſeneſſe and flux of the belly, or who undergo ſome indigeſtion, ought not to be blooded alſo the women with Childe ought to abſtain from it, principally in their firſt and laſt months: alſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121191:30"/>
thoſe who have uſed too great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety, thoſe who are of a cold and Phlegmatick Nature, and thoſe who Live in a Region or Air too cold or too hot, do not eaſily bear blooding. All things which weaken the powers, as horror and trembling, the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate uſe of venery, too great frequenting the bath, the flux of the belly whether it be by nature or Phyſick, great perplexity and care, watchings, and labour and tedious diſeaſes, do prohibit our uſe of blooding. For concluſion, whether to blood, or not to blood, All theſe things above mentioned, and ſeverall others, muſt be obſerved (which I ſhall here omit) for fear of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of writing any thing here, which hath been already long ago treated of by the more Learned: &amp; ſomuch more for that reading their writings I loſe my hopes
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121191:31"/>
of being able to ſay any thing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſubject, worthy to ſee the light.</p>
                  <p>All which would have been enough to have rendred my pen ſilent in this affaire, if the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the caſe, (which ought to be examined by divers writings,) together with a good will which doth move my affection to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in ſomething to ſerve in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique, had not imboldened me unto it. And alſo to leave unto poſterity ſome mark of my duty; And, that, as well, to ſolace and refreſh the Memory of my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in Chirurgery (giving them alſo ſome entrance into Aſtrologicall obſervation) which few among them know.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Charity of the Authour.</head>
                  <p>As alſo, for the health and benefit of thoſe who are to be blooded, having alwayes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred, the health of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121191:31"/>
poor ſick perſons who need blooding, or thoſe who uſe it to preſerve themſelves from diſeaſes, before the ariving to my owne gain, and profit.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The great errour and Covetouſneſſe of ſome Phlebotomiſts.</head>
                  <p>Many of the Chirurgions of our time do let blood at all houres, at all times, at all ſeaſons and all ages, without conſidering the power and ſtrength of the party whom they Lance, (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced thereunto by this curſed deſire of gain) never taking heed to the accidents which may come upon thoſe who have bin blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, making evacuation of more blood then they ought, or elſe making operation upon the Member at the time wherein the <hi>Starre</hi> is ruling or predominant there; inſomuch that ſome are dead by reaſon of the undue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121191:32"/>
of this Remedy, which hath cut of the uſe off their life; or if they be not killed thereby, they have fallen into a prolonged weakneſſe, and their bodies are thereby cold, wan, and diſcoloured; and all this by the ignorance of the operant who will put himſelf to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this ſo noble help of Nature, without being provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of all thoſe things which are Neceſſary for him, as well gifts of the body and minde, as other externall Inſtruments.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Condition of the <hi>Phlebotomiſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>As to be young, well ſighted, to have a ſteady hand, and exerciſed unto <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> a good Anatomiſt to know the ſcituation of the veines, and of other parts of the body; for without that, he will be like unto a blinde man which cleaves wood. But it will not
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121191:32"/>
be from the matter to note here, that if the veines, ſhould not be apparent, in the morning, you muſt not breath them, until about one a Clock in the day, and then thoſe who are able to walk, let them uſe a little Exerciſe, and then the moſt occult, and Invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible veines (as one would ſay) will appear. But I have not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned this here, except onely concerning thoſe who have ſmall veynes, and covered, either with fleſh or fat; Alſo ſhall I not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the Chirurgion to fill the veines by rubbings or bathing of the Member in warme water, Ligatures, and aſſuring the ſick party not to put them to any pain, for it would be too Trivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>What Inſtruments are to be uſed in Phlebotomy.</head>
                  <p>But I ſhall ſay (to return to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121191:33"/>
our purpoſe) that the externall Inſtruments by which this ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation is to be accompliſhed, ſhall be good Lancets of ſeveral faſhions, Ligatures, Swathes, Boulſters, Red pouder, burnt lint, to ſtop the blood if there be need of it, or with Cotton Pulveriſed according as we have ſhewn in our <hi>[Chirurgie Chymique.]</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Default in Phlebotomiſts.</head>
                  <p>This default eſpecially is found in the greateſt part of the <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> of our age, <hi>viz.</hi> That, of the knowledge of that ſo excellent &amp; wonderfull Aſtrologie, without which it is as it were impoſſible to be able well to exerciſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or Chirurgery upon our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, which are by good right called a little world, for their having a great Sympathy with the great one, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter by the help of God; as alſo the obſervation that ought
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121191:33"/>
to be made in the Concurrence of the Starres, and the influence of them upon our bodyes, to the end that we may avoid thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy accidents which we ſee daily to happen to the ſhare of thoſe who have been blooded ſo inconſideratly. That which hath withdrawn me from picking and culling out, all the conditions requiſite in this operation, as well for the Chirurgion as for the ſick perſon, and other things requiſite thereupon, is, I not having intended to treat on this ſubject, except of the two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall points of this operation, under which two may be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended all the reſt, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will explain them. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding I ſhall content my ſelf to have traced this little path for ſome one who (indued with a more high Style, and accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed with a greater knowledge,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121191:34"/>
provoked by one leſſe then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,) ſhall have had a deſire to have the knowledg of this ſcience appear (above the ſmall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which it hath pleaſed the divine goodneſſe to give me) and to make the deſires and lovers of true and perfect Chirurgery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers thereof; Provoked (I ſay) by this deſire, doth ſtretch out his ſayles of Eloquence to ſteere in a higher or greater Sea then I do. But winding up the thread of my diſcourſe, I ſhall content my ſelf, (I ſay) with theſe two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Points, that is to ſay, the time of Neceſſity and the time of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The time of neceſſity from whence taken.</head>
                  <p>That of Neceſſity is in all times and ſeaſons, and at all houres, without conſidering any thing which may hinder, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that the Neceſſity be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121191:34"/>
known to be the moſt ſtrong or preſſing, as I ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in its place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The time of Election from whence taken.</head>
                  <p>That of Election, is taken ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the nature of the body of the party who ought to be blooded, or of ſuperiour, and external things; which ought to be a fair clear and clean day, and not Rainy, not by no meanes at new Moon, nor very near to the full. And rather in the ſpring then any other ſeaſon. I ſhall declare alſo upon what parts of our bodyes the Planets and heavenly Signes do particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly rule; alſo in what day or hour, in what time or ſeaſon; To the end that having the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of theſe things one may not commit ſo many errours in this operation, as are committed by the ignorant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121191:35"/>
                  <head>Proteſtation of the Authour.</head>
                  <p>Proteſting that I have not writ this Tract poſſeſſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other deſire but to aſſiſt and help ſo many diſeaſed perſons, who dye for want of being well comforted by this excellent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and not to receive any glory thereby. But if I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome one ſpark, I do Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate and dedicate it from hence forward to the Authour of all things. To whom, Father Son and holy Spirit, be glory, honour and praiſe, for ever, and ever, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121191:35"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> How the Chirurgion ought not to be Ignorant of Aſtrologie, and the profit that proceeds there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from, as well for <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> as for all the diſeaſes which happen to humane bodies, The Sympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Starres therewith, and other diſcoveries moſt profitable to <hi>Chirurgions.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr good cauſe did the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mique Poet pronounce this Sentence, which is worthy of great conſideration, (to wit) That there is nothing more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable then the ignorant man, who eſteems nothing good, but the things which he doth himſelf, and of which onely, he hath knowledge. The which I make mention of here, by reaſon
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121191:36"/>
of a Crue of <hi>Sophiſters,</hi> who dare contradict the force which the ſuperiour bodyes have upon infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, alleadging that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients never took heed to theſe fooliſh fancies as they call them, (which they urge) being ignorant that the great <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> did Prognoſticate the plague which was to happen to the <hi>Iyllnians.</hi> And that, onely by the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which he had of this Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and divine ſcience of Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy: By that meanes preſerving a great number of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Greece, who in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of one ſo great bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, did give and attribute unto him great honours, which he dedicated to <hi>Hercules.</hi> Beſides having not read that the ſame <hi>Hippocrates</hi> reſtoring and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Phyſick, did ſo far praiſe and reſpect Aſtrologie, that he hath demonſtrated by knowledge, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121191:36"/>
concluded by reaſon, that Phyſick is maimed without the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Aſtrology, inſomuch that the <hi>Athenians</hi> after his death cauſed his image to be engraven, after they had built the Notable Colledges, for Phyſick and Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy Lectures. <hi>Plin. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Ch.</hi> 37. And particularly for one <hi>Beroſus</hi> a great Aſtrologian, after the death of whom was erected (in the Colledg of <hi>Athens</hi>) a Statue having a tongue of Gold, by reaſon of his Eloquence and great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Aſtrology. St. <hi>Jerome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Paulinus</hi> affirmes the profit of Phyſick, Aſtronomy, and Aſtrology, for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of mankinde. St. <hi>Dennis</hi> the <hi>Areopagite,</hi> by meanes of this Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, had knowledge of the death and paſſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Beſides, it is ſufficiently proved in the holy Scripture. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. where it is held forth
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121191:37"/>
that future events may be predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the order of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, even the faire and rainy dayes, as alſo in St. <hi>Matthew, (St.</hi> Matthew, <hi>Ch.</hi> 16.) The whole text whereof I had inſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted had I not feared to weary the Reader, and ſhould produce many other Authorities, and examples drawn from the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the Church, (which the moſt ſtudious could finde out) to cheque the preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, ignorance of the envious: for none can doubt of the verity and neceſſity of this Science, which cauſed <hi>Lycurgus</hi> the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonian</hi> to cauſe, that in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the courſe of the Starrs ſhould be obſerved, and to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain by expreſſe Law that the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conians</hi> ſhould not go to warre before the full of the Moon. That Grand <hi>Legiſlator, Moſes,</hi> had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121191:37"/>
the perfection of this Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as doth teſtifie the <hi>Proto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>martyr,</hi> Saint <hi>Steven,</hi> in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles. And a fore <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> the great Patriarch, <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> did eſteem it in the Land of the <hi>Chaldeans:</hi> as alſo the <hi>Lybians, Indians,</hi> and <hi>Sages</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by St. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Auntients great Aſtrologers.</head>
                  <p>Which is more; Do we not read that <hi>Pericles</hi> King of the <hi>Athenians</hi> and Emperour, delivered, his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my which was in Amazement from the Eclipſe of the Sun, and this onely by the onely Science of Aſtrology, the practiſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if <hi>Ilicias</hi> had had, he had not loſt his fair Triumphant Army in <hi>Sicily,</hi> being diſcomfited by a like motion. Which wound was not ſmall to the <hi>Athenians,</hi> but the beginning of infinite mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121191:38"/>
In ſhort, to the end that ſuch evils ſhould not fall on the <hi>Romans, Sulpitius Gallus</hi> did prognoſticate the Eclipſe of the Moon, long time before, to the end that his horſemen ſhould not be affrighted, and loſe their courage by ſeeing theſe things: which are ſufficient teſtomies to ſhew, that this Science was known by the Ancients, as well Phyſitians, as Kings, Princes, and other great Perſonages, which I omit for brevity ſake, to the end that I may produce that excellent book of <hi>Guidon</hi> of <hi>Caulias,</hi> whereof our Chirurgions do make ſo great a Trophy. But it is onely to keep it in their cloſet, or to make it keep the ſhop; for if they did read attentively the moſt profitable diſcoveries made therein, they would learn that then when he ſpeakes of the Superiour Root, and the inferiour
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121191:38"/>
Root in his Treatiſe of <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> that he underſtands or meanes by the Superiour Root, no other thing but that the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion be adviſed in times of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, to know and chooſe what Planet or what Heavenly ſigne concurs, in that time or in ſuch an hour wherein he would make his operation. Alſo that he know, whether the Star that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns the part, be there in the the ſame time, to the end to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate or diſcover the ſtrange Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, which might be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by death or great diſeaſes, as <hi>Ptolemie</hi> ſaith in the twenty ſixth Propoſition. But they will ſay; This would be very good if there were a meanes to learn all theſe things in a ſhort time. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that our life is very ſhort, &amp; the Art very long, as the Prince of Pyhſiticians <hi>Hippocrates</hi> hath well obſerved. <hi>Hip. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Aph.</hi> 1.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121191:39"/>
                  <head>Ex quovis ligno non fit Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius.</head>
                  <p>It is true, I agree with you: behold here the reaſon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all wood is not fit to make an Image of <hi>Mercury</hi> of. Since thou doſt acknowledge thy ſelf not to be fit to comprehend all that which is neceſſary to be known to a good Chirurgion, why doeſt thou not forbear to exerciſe this ſo excellent, and ſo admirable (yea more divine then humane) Science of Chirurgery, knowing well that we ſhall ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Accompt before God of all our Actions. And it will not then ſerve for excuſe to ſay, You had not a meanes to exerciſe any other calling, having had ſome entrance in this. And what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe is it, to make a beard for a Peaſant though with a thouſand
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121191:39"/>
ſcratches? to pull out a tooth, with a thouſand pain? to know how to ſpread a Plaiſter like a <hi>Plaiſterer</hi> or <hi>Maſon?</hi> and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other miſeries, which are committed by the malicious ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of many, all which I leave, that I may not be ſeen to go out of the line of my diſcourſe, And ſay that beyond the great profit that Chirurgions do gather from the knowledge of Aſtrologie in this operation called <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my;</hi> It ſerveth yet very much to the healing of diſeaſes, which come upon our bodies, alſo for gathering of Plants, and to dig out the Mettalls and Mineralls out of the bowels of the earth; of which one may prepare by the Art of <hi>Alchimy,</hi> moſt healthfull remedies; and adminiſter them to the diſeaſes which come into our bodies, by the mixtion or meeting of the three principall
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121191:40"/>
ſimples, whereof all bodies are Compoſed, (to wit) <hi>Sulphur Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Salt;</hi> from which three ſubſtances, all the diſeaſes that proceed there from are called by their proper names, as <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phereous, Mercuriall,</hi> and <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine:</hi> the which not making to this matter are contained in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Volume. <hi>In his Little Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall Chirurgery.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſome one will aske me why are ſuch names given to all diſeaſes; Making this queſtion, becauſe they are ignorant (as they confeſſe it publikely) of the three firſt ſubſtances, whereof all bodies are compoſed, which are (as we have ſaid) <hi>Sulphur, Salt</hi> and <hi>Mercury.</hi> Which ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>Hippocrates. Hip. Lib. de vet. med.</hi> Doth call in man; Bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Sweet, Salt and Moiſt: One whereof, (to wit) the Moiſt as being more apparant, he hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121191:40"/>
into four parts, which he calls Blood, Choller, Flegme, and Melancholy which is but the third part of that which conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes the matter. And which alſo gives us to know the diſeaſes growing by its depravation. <hi>Lib. de Genit.</hi> But the two others, his being ſilent, or letting them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone neglected hath buried the knowledge of diſeaſes which are of their eſſence, which is the reaſon they are held incurable, if they do not determine by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Theſe three ſubſtances are demonſtrative, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence may be Anatomized; but the four humours, not. Which things, or the like cauſed that pretty ſentence to be pronounced by <hi>Fabius,</hi> that the Arts and Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences would be happy, if there were none but wiſe and good unfolders, who ſhould give the judgment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:121191:41"/>
                  <head>The Common opinion of heading, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</head>
                  <p>But to anſwer and clear up what is above mentioned, I ſay, that it is materiall, not onely to know them in their true Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, with their originall and cauſe; but alſo, to give under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what ought to be the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, and the nature of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments neceſſary for their cure: ſo that the Common opinion doth not pleaſe me in any wiſe, which ſaith, Diſeaſes are cured by their contraries. That is to ſay, the hot diſtempers by cold Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments, and the cold ones by the hot, be it either in ſuch or ſuch a degree; which doth not ſeem unto me any way conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. But rather regard ought to be had above all things, to the ſpecifique virtue of Medicines, againſt every diſeaſe, becauſe to heale well, one need not take
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121191:41"/>
great paines upon accidents, (As one who would extinguiſh the fire, doth not take paines a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſmoake,) becauſe the diſeaſe being taken away, the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents diſcontinue. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if the Accidents ſurpaſſe the diſeaſe, in this caſe one leaves the diſeaſe to take heed to the Accidents, as in the great Haemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragie (or flux of blood at the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament:) Oh thou ſecond <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> (divine <hi>Paracelſus</hi>) what great obligation have we unto thee; but rather, what obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have we not unto thee! for having conducted us even to the perfection of Phyſick. If the Learned <hi>Galen</hi> were living, I am certain he would ſay, (ſeeing the Bookes of <hi>Parracelſus</hi>) as he did formerly when he ſaw the books of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> [Let us begin at them.] And I believe that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of diſparaging them, (as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121191:42"/>
many Jack-Apes do,) he would give an entire explanation of them; which Apes, neither will nor can, take the paines to finde out new remedies, for the poor afflicted ſick perſons. Therein do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as a bad Shoomaker ſhooing e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ery man by the ſame Laſt: for in truth I am confident, there is a Thouſand and a Thouſand of thoſe who ſay, that a hot remedy muſt be uſed to a cold diſeaſe, who know not to render a reaſon wherefo e it ſhould be ſo done. But I will inſiſt upon this, and do ask, Wherefore names are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſimple vegetalls, which do alſo belong to ſeverall parts of our bodies, As the little Leaves and flowers of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thonie</hi> to the head. <hi>Mirabolans, Citerinae; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluga,</hi> or <hi>Sorrell;</hi> and <hi>Mellifol,</hi> or <hi>Baulme,</hi> to the heart. The <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaria</hi> or <hi>Lungwort,</hi> to the Lungs. The <hi>Hepatica Lichen</hi> or
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121191:42"/>
Liver-wort, and the <hi>Jecoraria</hi> to the Liver. The <hi>Aſpelnum</hi> to the Spleene. The <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbilicus Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> for the Navell. The <hi>Calamus Aromaticus,</hi> and <hi>Caſſia fiſtula,</hi> for the Inteſtins. The <hi>Veſicaria</hi> for the Bladder. To the hands, the <hi>Palma Chriſti.</hi> The <hi>Plantain</hi> or <hi>five-Nerve,</hi> to the Nerves. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vina</hi> to the Veines. For the <hi>Tibia,</hi> and the bones, <hi>Legeranium Oſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſana.</hi> Mace, for the <hi>Matrix.</hi> For the Teeth, <hi>Dentaria:</hi> For the Throat, the <hi>Cervicaria</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> To the eares, the Leaves of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſari,</hi> and ſo of others. Will you anſwer me, That becauſe they have ſome kinde of agreement with thoſe parts, that therefore by conſequence, they have ſome kinde of property contrary to the <hi>Maladies</hi> that ſeize upon ſuch parts. Courage! I will wager, (oh rejoyce, the Ape who ſought to devour this holy Science is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121191:43"/>
his own ſelf) that he cannot eſcape. But tell me, conſider a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the qualities of theſe ſimples, with the cauſe of the <hi>Maladies</hi> that happen in theſe parts, and you ſhall find, That men have not amuſed themſelves to give names to theſe Plants, for any cauſe but the <hi>Sympathy</hi> which they have with them, giving re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief and ſuccour to thoſe parts, when wrought upon by diſeaſes or Maladies. And this is done by the property which they have to drive out ſuch or ſuch a Maladie, and ſtrengthen the part affected; and not by reaſon of their heat or cold. And therefore it is that we ſee in Peſtilent feavours, they give ſome <hi>Theriaque</hi> or <hi>Methridate</hi> which are of a hot quality, having in no wiſe reſpect to the Feavor which is cauſed by heat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:121191:43"/>
                  <head>Medicaments prepared by Chymical art, are more wholſome then Common ones.</head>
                  <p>But to the end that ſuch Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines be powerfull, well tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and altogether friendly to Nature, recourſe muſt be had to Quint-eſſences very dexteriouſly extracted from every compoſt, whether <hi>Vegetall, Animall,</hi> or <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> according to the ſpecific; virtue which nature hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to every one of them reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively. The ſame thing might I ſay as to Metalls: for, what meanes this pleaſant harmonie, with the heavenly bodyes? if they had not ſome agreement one with the other; as alſo of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall parts of our bodies, with the Caeleſtiall, and the Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:121191:44"/>
                  <head>The Harmony which the heavenly bodies, have with our humane bodies.</head>
                  <p>As the Sun in the middle of the 7. Planets; ſo is the heart (which is ſubject to it) placed in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or man, for the firſt and laſt mover, having within it ſelf the Artery beating without reſt; which is the Ecliptique of the Zodiack: (wherein the Sun con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues without rendring it ſelf Erratick), which hath as a cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to its ſpheare, the Navell, and the Continent thereof, and from the Groynes to the Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culary bones, the neck Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and lends to the Maſſe this part of the Lyliaſte, called vitall power. And as the Sun is the moſt excellent above all Planets, in like manner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo he hath agreement with the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121191:44"/>
moſt excellent of all Metall, <hi>viz.</hi> Gold.</p>
                  <p>Let us proceed and ſpeak of <hi>Saturn</hi> the Center of whoſe Spear is in the Arteryes, and who hath for its Region the Cavity of the Conduits, the Ligaments, Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, Marrow, Joynts, the bone of the head, the forehead, the hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of the eyes, and the upper part of the Noſe; and for its en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire body, the Spleen: and there placeth the receptive faculty, and hath <hi>Sympathy</hi> with Lead, as his true Legitimate Child.</p>
                  <p>Let us come to <hi>Jupiter</hi> who hath for his Sphericall Center the Lungs, and for its Region the windpipe, Trache, or Artery, the Muſcles ſerving for reſpiration, and the Skin of the head, and from him his naturall virtue hath Communication with Tynn.</p>
                  <p>Let us ſpeak of <hi>Mars,</hi> who hath for his Center the bagg of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121191:45"/>
the Gall, and for Region to his Sphere, hath the face from the eyes downwards; the palms of the hands, the ſoal of the foot and the neck of the Matrix, where he ſowes the Iraſcible and expulſive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and adjoynes to Iron.</p>
                  <p>Then <hi>Venus</hi> extends her rule and her Sphear upon the veſſells deſtined to generation, and gives the Concupiſcible faculty and pleaſant tickling doth Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate her power to Copper.</p>
                  <p>Afterwards comes the Sphear of <hi>Mercury,</hi> which ſpreads it ſelf in the interiour of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack, compriſed in the Superiour Orifice, wherein fear hath its place, and ſorrow in the Inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and laughter in the ſmall Guts, and for Center to its Spheare hath the Liver; where he plants the <hi>Fantaſtique</hi> virtue, and hath power over Quick-ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:121191:45"/>Laſtly, The Moon poſſeſſeth the bone of the back, the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the Loynes or vertue in venery; and retaines for entire body, Brain, giving the growing virtue or power, and having Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver for her Inferiour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>You muſt draw Metalique Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, for the Maladies of the ſame kinde.</head>
                  <p>And it happening that one of thoſe parts become depraved, it appears, and is made known in the place of its <hi>Emuncter,</hi> and then I pray will it not be neceſſary to extract Remedies from Metalls, to heale Metalique diſtempers without inquiring ſophiſtically, whether they be hot or cold di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes. Wherefore it is, that we ſee <hi>Mercury</hi> to be the true <hi>Alexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pharmacon,</hi> of the poyſon of the Pox; being as it were like in qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121191:46"/>
to the eſſence of this diſeaſe. But how much effectuall would it be, if the pure of it were ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from the impure.</p>
                  <p>From theſe things we do firſt learn to know the <hi>Metalique Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies,</hi> with their originall, when any of the inferiour parts of the body of man is diſeaſed; &amp; ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, from whence their moſt ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fique and Neigbouring <hi>Medicines</hi> ſhould be drawn, and thoſe of the greateſt virtue; which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt is from the ſeaven above named <hi>Mettalls,</hi> and from each of them being appropriated to its <hi>Malady,</hi> As to the diſeaſe of the heart, the <hi>Medicine</hi> of Gold muſt be taken: to the <hi>Maladies</hi> of the brain, the <hi>Medicine</hi> of Silver: to thoſe of the Liver, the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine</hi> of Quick-ſilver: to thoſe of the Lungs, the <hi>Medicine</hi> of Tin: to thoſe of the kidneys, the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine</hi> of Copper: and to thoſe of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121191:46"/>
the Call, the <hi>Medicine</hi> of Iron.</p>
                  <p>All which things are not of ſmall worth or conſequence, then when they are brought to the ſublime degree of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, the preparation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of lies onely in the art of <hi>Chymi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</hi> An Art truly divine, and whereof ſo many new perſons date give their opinions ſo leight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without knowing the very ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of it; Notwithſtanding their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance makes them calumniate this ſo admirable Art, for it is hard for a blinde man to judge of Colours. From hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the bodies here below are ruled by the Superiours, as true and Lawfull fathers of them. But in regard I have not intended to treat more largely of theſe things in this place, as not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to the ſubject taken in hand; and alſo in regard, as I have ſaid
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121191:47"/>
before, I do deſire (God aſſiſting me) to diſcourſe more amply of it in my Treatiſe, <hi>de Chyrurgie Chymique Medicinale. Reg.</hi> 2. <hi>Ch.</hi> 5. I ſhall pray all young <hi>Chirurgions</hi> withall my heart that they will lend an eare to theſe things, and embraſing my counſell to reject the old opinions, from whence we ſee ſo many miſeries are come, they being directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to true Phyſick: And let us not fear to be puniſhed like <hi>Aſa</hi> and <hi>Ochaſias</hi> for having rejected it, who ſuffered thereby.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Lib. de lege. Hippocrates</hi> ſaith of this time, that Phyſick was ſo be clouded by thoſe that exerciſed it, that it was ſlighted and reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as well by reaſon of their abuſe of it, as by the people who eſteemed them Phyſicians, and reputed them like unto Players, who by their geſtures and habits repreſent the perſons who they are not.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:121191:47"/>
                     <hi>In Epiſt. ad Democrit.</hi> The ſame <hi>Hippocrates</hi> confeſſeth of himſelf, that though he had at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto old age, he had not attained the end of Phyſick: ſince he doth acknowledge that he had not had the perfect knowledge of it, of neceſſity there reſts ſomething further to be known of it, To wit, whether he that ſhall find out the reſt, ought to be rejected.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Galen</hi> (6. <hi>de la Metho.</hi>) is not backard to give himſelf the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of having invented ſeverall <hi>Medicines</hi> unknown, and not in the practice of men before him. Let us not then reject <hi>Novelties,</hi> then, when they are for our bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and profit, if we may call <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veltie</hi> ſuch an Art as is as anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as <hi>Eſpugerie.</hi> In which, in truth, one can make no great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe being ignorant of Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, which is very requiſite and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121191:48"/>
neceſſary to this Chirurgicall operation, called <hi>Phelebotomy,</hi> conſidering which I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken this ſmall Treatiſe. For if our good Maſter <hi>Guidon,</hi> (of whom the whole <hi>Aca demique</hi> Schoole of Phyſick and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery make ſo great eſteem) hath not deſpiſed it, but, as he ſaith in his Treatiſe of <hi>Phlebotomie,</hi> hath made a whole book of it: which book is not to be found through the injury of the times, wherein he diſcourſeth at large of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Stars for this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; by much ſtronger reaſon we who pretend our ſelves his Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers ought not to ſleight it, but to imbrace and cheriſh it with all our heart, to the end that we may commit no errour in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming this operation.</p>
                  <p>This little Treatiſe will ſerve you therein, for a guide by meanes whereof you ſhall never fail or at
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121191:48"/>
leaſt not often, if you take heed thereunto, Culling and gathering out that which is worthy of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation: which doing, you will therefrom receive a great conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, according to God. To whom Father, Sonne, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, be honour, and glory, for ever, and ever, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the time of neceſſity, wherein are ſhewn the <hi>Maladies,</hi> in which <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> doth neceſſarily fall.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Chirurgery is the moſt certain part of Phyſick.</head>
                  <p>CHirurgery, being one of the moſt noble and comely parts of Phyſick, as well for its cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121191:49"/>
(for its operations are aſſured); as for that it hath been in all times exerciſed among the Greeks, by their Princes and great Lords, hath great extent, and containes many more things then the Vulgar people do ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. It is ordinarily divided in five parts. The firſt concerns Tumours, which the Common people call Apoſtumes, which are <hi>Maladies</hi> encreaſed in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and greatneſſe. The ſecond is of Wounds, which are defined to be, Diſſolving of continuity made in the ſoft parts, freſh and bleeding. The third is of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcers:</hi> and the fourth of fractures which belong to the bones. And the fifth and laſt of Luxations, which is when the bones are out of their naturall place.</p>
                  <p>All which <hi>Maladies</hi> in the cure of them do require the oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneſt, amongſt the remedies,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121191:49"/>
that of blooding, without which the cure of them cannot be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly accompliſhed, as alſo in ſeverall other ſorts of <hi>Maladies,</hi> which we ſhall name hereafter, wherein the neceſſity of <hi>Phlebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy</hi> is requiſite and neceſſary, Blooding may well ſerve in th' one and th'other, but it is not neceſſary unto them, but when neceſſity compells; We will here diſcourſe briefly of them all; to the end, that the young Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion may know what <hi>Maladies</hi> require blooding, and which not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In what <hi>Maladies</hi> blooding is uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</head>
                  <p>So that for a great pain in the head, which is in the hinder part of it, we Lance the veines of the forehead; in <hi>Squinancies,</hi> they breathe the veine under the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121191:50"/>
tongue. <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> is neceſſary to all affections or <hi>Maladies</hi> which take away the breath, and ſtrangle one; and to thoſe which cauſe one ſuddainly to looſe their ſpeech: Alſo to all great Contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions either of the internall or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall parts, as to full from on high or to receive a blow. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the power or force were but ſmall, and though the blood be peccant neither in quality not quantity, you muſt uſe the blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>What Delire is. Galen.</hi> 2. <hi>Aph.</hi> 2. In the Apoplexie, Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, Burning feaver, preſently and in the beginning of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lire,</hi> which is nothing but a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved and errant motion of the imagination, hurt; you muſt let blood, provided that the powers be ſtrong enough, and the age ſuffer it, and the ſeaſon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. <hi>Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>de Metho. Ch.</hi> 2. And although that be not yet
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121191:50"/>
provided that the power be a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſtrong. Alſo ſuch a one who after a fall vomits blood, you muſt blood preſently; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the blood may jelly or clott if one ſuffer it to reſt, and grow cold. You muſt not blood the ſick perſon in the Rigor of the ſeavor, for he that doth it, is the Cutter of his throat. But if the feavour doth not increaſe, and alſo doth not decreaſe, and we do not hope for any declination of it, in ſuch a caſe you muſt not loſe this onely oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of blooding, although it be worſe then in the declination of the fit. In the hand-gout and the foot-gout, one may open the veins of the foot or the hand; &amp; for the <hi>Migren</hi> the Arteries and veines of the Temples: and by this eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation of the blood, which flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with the Arthritique powers, and the boyling ſpirits, which evacuate, the pain preſently ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121191:51"/>
But in the intermitting fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, blooding ought to be not after the third acceſſe, or fit, as <hi>Galen</hi> would have it; but in the beginning: but this evacuation of the blood ought to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be if there be <hi>Plethory</hi> in the body, and fulneſſe of the veſſells: and for the breathing and refreſhing of the Maſſe of humors, for otherwiſe there ſhould be no evacuation of the blood, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the bridle of the Chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
                  <p>In the quartain feavour, or (again) if the blood do abound, you muſt take ſome from the <hi>Mediane</hi> or <hi>Baſilique</hi> of the left Arme, or from the ſplenique veine, with this Caution, that if the blood do ſhew it ſelf black and dull or thick, you may let it run, but on the contrary you muſt ſtop it pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ently, if it ſhew it ſelf freſh and well coloured.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:121191:51"/>In the cure of the <hi>Fehris Synochus,</hi> a continuall feavor, the benefit of <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> cauſes the opening of the belly, and the ſweatings to iſſue forth very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, a thing much to be wiſhed in this kinde of feaver, which moved <hi>Galen</hi> to ſay, that one ought to bleed in this caſe, even untill <hi>Lipothemie:</hi> but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding fearing that one ſhould let ſlip the ſoul with the blood, one ought rather to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterate it ſeverall times, as much as the ſtrength of the ſick party can bear it; even in the burning feaver, <hi>eſpece de Tierce continue,</hi> one ought to blood in a good quantity, if the powers, the age, and other Circumſtances do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
                  <p>In like manner, you ought to blood, in the quartain feaver, (Gliſtering firſt): for the doing whereof Artificially, you muſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121191:52"/>
open the veine of the left Arme, which hath more Communicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Spleen, to which the moſt part of this feaver is often heaped. We ſay alſo, that in Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilent feavers, we muſt not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently (as is done preſently when they ſee the perſon ſtrook with the plague) preſcribe him blooding, which hath been of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten times the cauſe of the death of an infinite Number of perſons: but if the matter be urgent in quantity, quality, and Motion, I muſt draw a concluſion, That in the Plague occaſioned by the viciouſneſſe of the Ayre, with fulneſſe of blood and humors; Blooding I ſay together with pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation are there neceſſary, which is held ſorth by the ſaying of <hi>Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Celſ. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 7. That foraſmuch as the Plague is an Active and Tempeſtative diſeaſe, you muſt quickly uſe remedyes even with raſhneſs,</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:121191:52"/>Wherefore you muſt conſider, if the perſon infected hath a burning feaver, and great repletion in the Conduits, and that the virtue be ſtrong, which may be known by the veins, being full and ſtretched, the eyes and the face greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, alſo ſometimes in ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting blood with great beating of the Arteries of the Temples, pain in the throat, pain or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in breathing, pricking or ſhooting throughout the body, with exceeding heavineſſe and dulneſſe, the waters or urine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing red, thick, and troubled, in ſuch caſe you muſt blood preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to help nature, to diſcharge her-ſelf, leaſt the naturall heat be ſuffocated by the aboundance of blood. Then you muſt rather breathe the <hi>Baſilique</hi> veine of the left ſide, then the right, becauſe the heart and the ſpleen are much
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121191:53"/>
affected in this diſeaſe, and take abundance of blood thence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as you ſhall ſee neceſſary, alwaies having reſpect to the power and virtue of the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and taking heed not to blood, whilſt the ſhivering of the feaver is upon him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obſervations in blooding, for the difference of the diſeaſe.</head>
                  <p>But you muſt here take notice, that in ſuch a repletion of blood, blooding muſt be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe performed in a ſimple Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſeaver, than in that which is accompliſhed with a <hi>Bubon</hi> or <hi>Carbuncle:</hi> for if the one, or both together be conjunct with the great and furious ſeaver, then it is requiſite to open the veine nearer to the Apoſtume, or plague ſoare, and according to the recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of feavers, to the end, that
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121191:53"/>
thereby the blood may be draw a forth, and evacuated directly, in regard that all retraction and Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulſion, of infected blood to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Noble parts, is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited by all good Phyſitians and Chirurgions. But enough of the feaver, untill we ſpeak of <hi>Sympto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques.</hi> And beginning at Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors in generall, I ſay, that if there be repletion in the whole body, you muſt purge and blood, and beſides makes frictions and Bathings. As in the Cure of the true <hi>Phlegmon,</hi> you muſt divert the flux, which will be turned away, if we take away the cauſe thereof, to wit, the <hi>Chachochi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> or <hi>Plethory,</hi> which is to be done by purging firſt, but chiefly by <hi>Phlebotomy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Come we now to the <hi>Eriſipela,</hi> for if it be in the face, and doth poſſeſſe it very much, <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> is very neceſſary to it, which muſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121191:54"/>
be performed upon the <hi>Cephali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que</hi> veine; in like manner <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy</hi> is neceſſary, if there be ſome portion of blood mingled with the Choller: but if it be in any other part, and be not in great quantity, and be made of pure Choller, <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> is not neceſſary, becauſe the blood is the Bridle of the Choller, as we have made mention before: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Cancre is cured moſt commonly by purging and <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the Tumors in particular being a <hi>Parotide,</hi> we ſay that <hi>Phleb.</hi> is therein very neceſſary, ſpecially when there is redneſſe in the part, which demonſtrates great inflammation &amp; abundance of blood, alſo for the kernells great, and ſwelled, you muſt purge, but ſpecially purge and apply Cupping-glaſſes, behind the ſhoulders with ſcarificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121191:54"/>
to the end to obviate the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which may come there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, as ſuffocation and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently Choaking.</p>
                  <p>The ſame remedy is neceſſary to the Tumor or inflammation, and relaxation of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>vula,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Latines <hi>Collumella.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo for Eſquinancy, the <hi>Chir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urgian</hi> ought to be ready and prompt, in reguard this diſeaſe doth not give great Leaſure, wherefore he muſt blood the ſick parts on the <hi>Baſilique</hi> on that ſide where the fluxion is, and the ſame day on the veines under the tongue to evacuate the Conjunct matter.</p>
                  <p>Let us ſpeak of Fellons, or whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, the curing whereof con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts onely in blooding and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; but yet notwithſtanding further according to the prudence of the good Chirurgion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:121191:55"/>Come we now to Wounds, wherein for the Little ones there is no great neceſſity of blooding; but in the great where there is danger of fluxion, or where the body is repleate, as in wounds of the Joynts, Tendon, Nerves, and where one fears paine, rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and inquietude; yea alſo when they are accompanied with a feaver. And as for the Spaſme coming in Wounds through re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletion, it muſt be cured by inanition, and that by the good government of purging food, and blooding, and for a reſolutive remedy, friction, and ſulphured bathes.</p>
                  <p>As to particular Wounds, if there happen in thoſe of the head, with fracture or contuſion, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued feaver, and Raveing with great flegmatique inflammation, accompanyed ſometimes with the hurting of the Pericrani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; tis
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121191:55"/>
then that you muſt take abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of blood, but yet therein the Chirurgion muſt conſider the ſtrength of the Patient, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the motion of the Brain, (the Chirurgion ſeeing that the bone is not fractured, but doubts that there is ſome veſſell broak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en within) let him preſently take ſome blood from the <hi>Cepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> veine, on that ſide is hurt, in a good quantity; having regard to the diſtemper, preſent and future, and principally of the ſtrength as I have ſaid before, and other things which ought to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in blooding.</p>
                  <p>You muſt take notice, that in wounds by Gun-ſhot, there doth not come forth much blood, wherefore the day after he muſt uſe revulſive <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> and take ſo much blood as is proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the fulneſſe of blood; and the ſtrength of the party; and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121191:56"/>
he muſt not fear to make averſion of the blood towards the noble parts, ſo long as in ſuch wounds there is no venemous quality.</p>
                  <p>As to that which concerns the blood of great Contuſions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the body, it muſt be evacuated either ſenſibly or inſenſibly, which inſenſible evacuation is done by bloodings, Cupping-glaſſes, or Scarrifications, or by Horſe-Leeches, and that upon the ſame day, or the next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>And unto this <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſeems to agree in his book of Fractures; in ſaying, if any one is fallen down from on high, the ſame day one ought to give him Phyſick or blood him: and <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> ſaith upon this ſubject, that if any one is fallen from an high place, although he have but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle blood, (or nor enough), It is ſo that ſome of that blood muſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121191:56"/>
be drawn from him to prevent it from coagulating and corrupting in the inner parts of the body, being out of his proper veſſells; and in the cure of the <hi>Gangreen,</hi> one part of its curing lies in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and blooding. If the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of the body be <hi>Plethorique</hi> or <hi>Cacochymicall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides, for curing the ſcald or Leproſy, if thoſe who are infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with ſuch a diſeaſe, be of a ſufficient age, they ſhall be blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and over and above purged and blooded.</p>
                  <p>In the cure of the <hi>Ophthalmie,</hi> or inflammation of the uppermoſt skin of the Eye, the Chirurgion muſt propoſe three points. The firſt is the regulating food. The ſecond is evacuation of the Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent matter. And the third is the application of Topicall medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caments: two of which I ſhall let alone, as not conducing to this
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121191:57"/>
ſubject; and ſhall onely ſay, that he who ought to evacuate the Antecedent matter, ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it by purgation and <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomie,</hi> and by Cupping-glaſſes, applyed to the ſhoulders, in like manner for the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngula.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the beginning of the curing, whereof you muſt uſe purgation and blooding; eſpecially if there be great inflammation.</p>
                  <p>And which is more in the cure of the <hi>Mydriaſis,</hi> which is no other thing but a dilatation of the pupill of the eye, either oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned naturally or by accident; its cure conſiſts in nothing but applying upon the eye, repercuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive things, and to appeaſe the dolour or pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and prohibit the defluxion by regular diet, but ſpecially by <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-glaſſes, frictions, and other things, which one ſhall ſee beni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:121191:57"/>For the pain in the Teeth oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by fluxion; one may let blood for evacuating the antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent matter, and all by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of a good Chirurgion.</p>
                  <p>In the preſervative cure of the Stone, eſpecially if there be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pletion, you muſt evacuate as well by Medicaments, as by <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> and vomiting, which is a ſingular remedy to prevent the Stone. And if one ſhould come to take it out, you ought to purge the patient well, and blood him two dayes after he hath taken the Phyſick.</p>
                  <p>In the ſmall Pox or Meaſles, diſeaſes which are very frequent in Children, you muſt in no wiſe blood them, unleſſe there be great plenitude, or ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of ſome diſeaſe, (as a <hi>Pluriſie, Ophthalmie, Eſquinancy,</hi> and ſuch like) or if it be not at the declination of the diſeaſe, or
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121191:58"/>
at leaſt the firſt or ſecond day of ſickneſſe, at the furtheſt.</p>
                  <p>But you muſt take notice, that in ſeveral <hi>Maladies,</hi> you muſt not attend untill the <hi>Malady</hi> appear, to the end, to uſe <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> afterwards, (as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith,) but you ought to foreſee it, blooding them in the Spring, as we ſhall diſcover in the Part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Election.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Neceſſity hath no ſet time for bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in.</head>
                  <p>Finally, for the Neceſſity to uſe <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> or not to uſe it; I ſay, that then when the diſeaſe requires it, and that neceſſity preſſeth, one may blood at all times, in all ſeaſons, and at all houres, be it night or day, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes conſidering the power and ſtrength of the patient, the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity and quality of blood taken
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121191:58"/>
out, carrying ones ſelf in all the <hi>Phlebotomique</hi> operations above inſtanced, with a ſound Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, accompanied with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and experience; In the contrary practice the Chyrurgion will very hardly arive to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed end, in regard that then when he ſhall underſtand it to be neceſſary to uſe <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> when the ſaving of ones life is in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute; and that he finds himſelf all alone, not able to conſult with any body, concerning the diſeaſe, he ought not to preſent before himſelf any obſtacles; whether of the quality or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Perſon, or for fear of making the operation without advice, for that will hinder him in making a good operation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe fear coming upon him, and cauſing his hand to tremble, is ſufficient to hinder ſuch an effect of the operation as we expect.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121191:59"/>
                     <hi>The</hi> Plebotomiſt, <hi>ought to be bold.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Times of Election divided into two.</head>
                  <p>Let us come now to the time of Election, which is divided by <hi>Guidon</hi> into two parts, (to wit) the inferiour Root, and the ſuperiour Root: meaning by the inferiour root; The diſpoſition of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, of the time, the Region, the Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tome, the force, and ſtrength, and ſo of others. And by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour Root; the obſervation in the Concu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4+ letters">
                        <desc>••••…</desc>
                     </gap> of the Starrs: which time of Election we ſhall deduce briefly, not having under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to diſcourſe of any other things here, ſave that. Yet, as I have ſaid before, I will do it as ſuccinctly as poſſibly I can, by the aſſiſtance of the grace of God. To whom father, ſon, and ſpirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:121191:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of the time of Election for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour root, and of the ſuperiour root, which reaches to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Starrs, as well in the concurrence which they have to the parts of our bodies, as upon the humours and <hi>Maladies</hi> which happen therein.</head>
               <p>THe Aſtrologicall Science is ſo admirable, that it hath cauſed all the Philoſophicall Phyſicians, as well Auntient as modern to ſay, that it is moſt neceſſary to <hi>Chirurgions,</hi> to have the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it; as well for the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and profit, which one may extract therefrom in ſeverall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, as for the neceſſity of knowing the concurrence of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121191:60"/>
Starrs upon the bodies, the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence whereof the Chirurgions ought to obſerve punctually upon our bodies, in all his operations, eſpecially in that of <hi>Phlebotomy.</hi> And all thoſe who have Treated thereof, have obſerved two times, as we have ſaid here before, (to wit) the time of Neceſſity, and the time of Election, in which time of neceſſity the Chirurgion will know how to regulate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, according to the diſcourſe before inſerted; Now it remains to ſpeak of the time of Election, which according to the doctrine of the good <hi>Guidon,</hi> we will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide into two parts, to wit, the Inferiour root, and the Superiour root.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Obſervation concerning the time of Election.</head>
                  <p>Now the Inferiour root may
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:121191:60"/>
be thus underſtood. Firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the concoction of the food, it muſt be throughly performed, before you let blood, (if you have eaten lately before): Alſo if ones blood be groſſe, it is neceſſary before bleeding, to uſe a little exerciſe for the ſubtiliſing the blood; or at leaſt that one take ſome kind of things which have the faculty of ſubtiliſing it, which are, the ſyrup of the herb Calamint, and ſuch like; In the ſecond place, one muſt conſider the force, and the ſtrength, the temperature and the neceſſity of him who ought to be blooded, to the end, that the re-iteration thereof be not perform'd ſooner, or latter, then is neceſſary, chooſing a ſerene day, and not ſubject to inconſtancy, clear and not dull not rainy, in the ſpring, and in <hi>Autumne,</hi> making choice alſo of a wind which is uncertain,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121191:61"/>
as if it be in Winter, you ſhould take a day wherein the ſouthwind blowes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Digreſſion.</head>
                  <p>But ſome one may demand here, If the winds have any power over our bodies, that we need to make obſervation of them. To which I anſwer, that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence lets us ſee the effects, which they produce upon our bodies, as the Plague, the <hi>Coqueluch,</hi> (a new diſeaſe which troubled the <hi>French</hi> in the year 1510 and 1557.) <hi>Pluriſie, Apoſthumes, Catharrs, Fluxions, ſmall Pox,</hi> and <hi>Scabbineſſe</hi> or the <hi>Itch:</hi> alſo ſo many venemous Creatures, as <hi>Froggs, Toades, Locuſts, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpillers, Spiders, Flyes, Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netons, Snayles, Serpents, Vipers, Snakes, Efts, Scorpions</hi> and <hi>Aſps.</hi> Yea in all hot and moiſt times,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:121191:61"/>
if the Southwind blow, Meats will Corrupt or taint in leſſe then two houres, let them be but freſh; wherefore one need not enter into doubt, that humane bodies enter in affections contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to nature, when the ſeaſons pervert their qualities, by the evil diſpoſition of the Ayre, and the winde that is mingled within them. Unto this I will adjoyn, that which the great <hi>Hippocrates</hi> hath truly pronounced.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hip. in his preface of Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, and</hi> Galen <hi>in his Comment.</hi> [That the Ayre hath (I know not what) of divine in it ſelf] in regard that it doth (in blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing through the Univerſall World) incompaſſe all things contained within it, and doth nouriſh them miraculouſly; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaines and ſupports them firmly, and entertaines them in an Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable union; the whole Symbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121191:62"/>
with the Starrs, into which the Divine providence is infuſed; which changeth the Ayre accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his pleaſure, &amp; gives unto it power as well over the mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of times as the naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. And therefore the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> and <hi>Phyſicians</hi> have expreſly commanded us to have reſpect to the ſcituation of places, and to the Conſtitution of the Ayre, and concurrence of the Starrs, when you are in agitation for the preſerving of health; Or to cure the ſick, in which caſes the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and change of the Ayre is very powerfull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hip. his third book of Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes Ch.</hi> 5. and 17. The ſame <hi>Hippocrates</hi> affirmes our bodies, do receive great alteration by the viciſſitude of the times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the year, as by the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne winde, which doth render us ſubjected to all ſorts of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies,</hi>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121191:62"/>
which acknowledge moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture for their firſt cauſe, and it doth infeeble our naturall heat, which (in the oppoſite caſe of a cold and dry winde) doth forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it ſelf, and is rendred more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, and doth in like manner render our ſpirits more Subtill and Active.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A prety obſervation, upon the winds and our bodies.</head>
                  <p>Beſides, there is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to the four principall windes, four Elements, four hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, four ſeaſons, and four ages. The South winde or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter doth in quality participate with Tender years, then to fire and Choler, and alſo to Summer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auſtraphricus,</hi> or a midle wind betwixt <hi>Auſter</hi> and <hi>Africus,</hi> participates of the ſtronger years, of the Ayre, of the blood, and the ſpring.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:121191:63"/>
                     <hi>Subſolanus,</hi> or Eaſt wind, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tes of the more Grave years, of water, Flegme and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Favonius,</hi> or Weſt wind, to the more decrepit and decayed yeares, to the Earth, the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholique humour, and to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhould have inſiſted lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon the property of the windes, but that I have treated ſufficiently of it in another place, In his Book call'd <hi>Grande Chirurg.</hi> and have only ſpoken of it here, to ſhew how they have power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Bodies; and therefore, not out of rule or order, if we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them in <hi>Phlebotomie E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective.</hi> But returning to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, we ſay, that if the Veins be ſmall, you muſt ſtay till ten of the Clock in the morning, for at that time, they appear better then at ſix a Clock: ſuch are the veins of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121191:63"/>
the Tongue, of the hands, and the feet; obſerving alſo to let blood in the winter, on the left ſide or part; and in Summer on the right, as ſaith <hi>Guidon.</hi> The reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is, ſaith he, becauſe the humors which at thoſe times, we endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to evacuate, are properly in thoſe parts; it being true alſo, that the cold humors do rule moſt in the left part, and the hot hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours in the right: behold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, why in Winter (which is cold) we draw blood from the left part, and in the Summer from the right.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Region must be obſerved in blooding.</head>
                  <p>In like manner, the natural ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of the Body ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in the emptying it of blood; for we do largely empty thoſe who have large veins, and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121191:64"/>
who are not too lean, nor too whitely or pale; nor have their fleſh too tender; but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, we do leſs empty thoſe who have but little blood, and the fleſh tender: in like manner, you muſt have reſpect to the Region; for if it be very warm, as it is in <hi>France,</hi> the Countrey of <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc,</hi> and <hi>Provence,</hi> in this place, you muſt make no great evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the like muſt be obſerved in the cold Region, becauſe that the natural heat being emptied out with the blood, the Region doth chil the body too much, and the hot Region by its heat, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitate the ſtrength, for this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reaſon, the Summer ſeaſon, nor the Winter, are not in any wiſe, fit to breathe a vein in, but the moſt proper time, is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Spring, (becauſe it is temperate) breathing the vein in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121191:64"/>
the morning, (not immediately) upon your wakening.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, you muſt conſider the former life of the Patient to wit, whether he you are to blood, have uſed great quantity of meats or drinks, principally, of ſuch, as give great nouriſhment; for if ſo one may blood them boldly, but (if on the contrary) not ſo much; notwithſtanding, to thoſe, who are too full of exces, and are drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards voluptuous, or Gourman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizers, never put your hand; for truly, one doth not help them much, by taking blood from them, becauſe by their intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, they immediately heap up abundance of humors.</p>
                  <p>Alſo one ought not neg igent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to let ſlip the Cuſtom of bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for thoſe who have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> themſelves to it, do undergo it better then thoſe who have not: ſo that by very good r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121191:65"/>
one may blood thoſe, who have loſt the benefit of evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of excrements, by having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born accuſtomed exerciſe.</p>
                  <p>But enough hath been ſpoken concerning the inferior Root, let us ſpeak now concerning the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior; for as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith, <hi>(in Libro de Criticis diebus)</hi> and alſo as <hi>Philoſophy</hi> ſaith, The infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or World is governed by the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior, ſo that it is neceſſary for Chirurgions, to conſider the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the ſeven Planets, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of the Signes, and other hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bodies, to the end, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the knowledge thereof, he may take heed of blooding in the part which is poſſeſſed by one of theſe Signes; which Planets and Signes, we will put in order, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the parts of the Body which they poſſeſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:121191:65"/>
                  <head>Upon what maladies the Planets rule.</head>
                  <p>In the firſt place, <hi>Saturn</hi> cold and dry, hath reſpect unto the melancholique humour, and upon the maladies compoſed of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and by conſequence, rules over the Spleep.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jupiter</hi> hot and moyſt, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the blood, and upon the maladies cauſed by blood, and from that reaſon, governs the Liver.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mars,</hi> hot and dry, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Choller, and upon Chollerique Diſeaſes, and by this meanes, governs the <hi>Cystis fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sol,</hi> hot and dry, governs the Heart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Venus,</hi> cold and moyſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends her power upon the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels appropriate to generation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:121191:66"/>
                     <hi>Mercury,</hi> of a temperate Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion, is indifferent to all the humours.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luna,</hi> cold and moyſt, hath power principally upon the Phlegme, and Phlegmatique ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies, ſhe rules in the brain; but her power is extended much fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in that which concerns her property for elective blooding; for ſhe being delivered from her hindrance, and in Conjunction with <hi>Jupiter Venus</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the ſixth, third, and fourth op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, in her own ſign, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent for blooding.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Aſpects of the Stars ought to be obſerved in blooding.</head>
                  <p>On the contrary, it is not good to let blood, the Moon being in <hi>Leo,</hi> or in 12 degrees before, or after the Dragon; and principally, you muſt take heed, that <hi>Saturn</hi> be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121191:66"/>
neither in oppoſition to, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with her, or <hi>Gemini</hi> with <hi>Mars;</hi> for ſuch Aſpects are very dangerous, but the Moon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in conjunction with the three Planets above mentioned, which is <hi>Jupiter, Venus,</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> it is very good: <hi>Piſces</hi> and <hi>Sagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarius</hi> for the Phlegmatiques: the firſt part of <hi>Libra,</hi> for the Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholique: for the Chollerique <hi>Cancer</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries, which are <hi>Leo,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of <hi>Libra,</hi> and the firſt of <hi>Scorpio:</hi> the others are indifferent and mean for <hi>Phlebotomie;</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, we will ſpeak more particularly thereof hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Diviſion of the times of the Moon.</head>
                  <p>But here it is worthy of obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, that the Moon, (the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121191:67"/>
of humours) is divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to four parts: The firſt is from the Conjunction, or new Moon, unto the firſt quarter, ſignified by <hi>Gemini,</hi> which continues ſeven dayes, wherein it is good to blood young Children.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond, is, from <hi>Gemini,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Oppoſition, which is the full Moon, 7. dayes more, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is good to blood the young and active, about the age of 20. or 30. years.</p>
                  <p>The third, is from the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the laſt part of <hi>Gemini</hi> when you may blood the ſtrong and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, from 30. to 60. years.</p>
                  <p>The fourth part of the Moon, is the laſt 7. dayes of her laſt <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> wherein you muſt blood the decaying, who are above 50. years old, only in caſes of neceſſity; but in whatſoever Aſpect the Moon be, you muſt not make inciſion on any member, nor touch it with
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121191:67"/>
any Inſtrument or Cauterizer, either actual or potential, if the Moon be in the Signe, ruling that member: You muſt take notice, that the third quarter is beſt for <hi>Phlebot.</hi> Beſides, the firſt quarter is hot and moyſt, the ſecond, hot and dry; the third, cold and moyſt, and the fourth cold and dry; 'Tis true, that at all times, the Moon is effectively cold and moyſt; but in her ſeveral quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſhe doth acquire ſeveral Complexions, according to the ſeveral Aſpects of the Sun, ſo that we ſay, Every one ought to be blooded, in that quarter where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he hath moſt agreement, or likeneſs; and the firſt quarter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins after the Conjunction of the Moon with the Sun. But you muſt here take notice, that by Conjunction we mean, when the Sun and Moon are in the ſame Signe: And by oppoſition, or full
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121191:68"/>
Moon, we mean, when the Moon is in one Signe, and the Sun is in an oppoſite Sign in the half of the Zodiac.</p>
                  <p>But the Aſpects of the Moon are <hi>Conjunction, Oppoſition, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drate, Trine</hi> and <hi>Sextile,</hi> marked by the Aſtrologers, after this manner.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conjunction</hi> in this manner. ☌</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Oppoſition</hi> thus. ♂</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Quadrate.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Trine.</hi> 
                        <g ref="char:trine">△</g>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sextile.</hi> ⚹</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The propriety of the twelve Signes, upon the humane bodies.</head>
                  <p>Beſides, we conſider in the eighth Sphere, which is the Starry Heaven, (and which is called the Zodiac) twelve Signs; whereof three are of the nature of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:121191:68"/>
fire, which are <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> proper for Phlegma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique perſons, (except in the burning parts above mentioned) Signes which paſſe by eight De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, unto the thirteenth degree of <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> and doth ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the attractive faculty.</p>
                  <p>The other three are of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of water, to wit, <hi>Cancer, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> very proper for cholerick perſons, good to comfort the expulſive faculty, and to adminiſter Laxative Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick.</p>
                  <p>The other three, of the nature of Earth, which are <hi>Taurus, Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Capricorn,</hi> very good to ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine perſons, and good to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the retentive faculty.</p>
                  <p>The other three, participate of the Ayr, to wit, <hi>Gemini, Libra,</hi> and <hi>Aquarius:</hi> theſe are very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet for melancholy perſons, and good to cheriſh the digeſtive fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty.
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121191:69"/>
But for the knowing upon what parts of our Bodies the ſaid Signes do rule, we will ſet it down in order; to the end, that the Chirurgion commit no er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror therein; for the day and hour wherein they concur, you muſt have recourſe to ſome good Almanack, Ephemeris, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Ephemerides of <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan,</hi> which will continue yet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the year 1660.</p>
                  <p>You muſt take notice here, that I ſend you to the Epheme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, to know in what day, hour, degree and minute, the Sign will rule; for it is out of my deſign, to teach it you here, or to know their Aſcendant Conjunction, or Oppoſitions, good or bad, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in my Book called <hi>(Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Chirurgerie)</hi> I ſpeak of it large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough, wherefore I ſay, you ſhall have recourſe to the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merides: In the mean time, I
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121191:69"/>
will perſue the declaring upon what parts of the body the Stars do rule, with their proprieties. And in the firſt place, <hi>Aries</hi> is hot and dry, of the nature of fire, he governs the head and face of a man; and it is good to blood, when the Moon is there, unleſſe it be in the part which the Moon governs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The parts wherein the Signes rule together, with their property concerning blooding.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Taurus</hi> is cold and dry, of the nature of the Earth, and governs the neck and Wind-pipe; and it is bad to make uſe of bleeding, the Moon being in that Sign.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gemini</hi> is hot and moyſt, of the nature of Ayr, and governs the ſhoulders and Arms, and hands; is ill for blooding.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:121191:70"/>
                     <hi>Cancer</hi> is cold and moyſt, of the nature of water, and governs the Breaſt, the ſtomach &amp; Lungs, and is indifferent: neither too good, nor too bad for blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Leo</hi> is hot and dry, of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of fire, and governs the back and ſides, and is ill for blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Virgo</hi> is cold and dry, of the nature of the Earth, governs the Belly and the Intrals, is neither very good, nor bad for blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Libra</hi> is hot and moyſt, of the nature of the Ayr, and governs the Navel, the Reins, and the lower part of the Belly; good to blood in.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Scorpio</hi> is cold and moyſt, of the nature of water, and governs the parts for generation, is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor bad.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:121191:70"/>
                     <hi>Sagittarius</hi> is hot and dry, of the nature of fire, and governs the Thighes; is good to let blood,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aquarius</hi> is hot and moyſt, of the nature of Ayr, and governs the Legs; is neither good nor bad for letting blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Piſces</hi> is cold and moyſt, of the nature of water, governs the Feet; and is neither good nor bad to let blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aries, Libra,</hi> and <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> are very good; <hi>Virgo, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Aquarius</hi> and <hi>Piſces,</hi> are indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; <hi>Taurus, Gemini,</hi> and <hi>Leo,</hi> and <hi>Capricorn,</hi> are evil.</p>
                  <p>Yet we ſay, that the Moon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Trixe,</hi> and <hi>Sextile</hi> with <hi>Venus,</hi> it is a good time to purge Choller by Electuary; with the Sun, 'tis good to purge Flegme by drinks with <hi>Jupiter,</hi> 'tis good to purge melancholy by Pills.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:121191:71"/>
                  <head>Diviſion of the Signes.</head>
                  <p>Furthermore, you muſt take notice, that every one of the Signes, is divided into 30. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, from whence it followes, that in the whole Zodiac, there are 360. degrees; and again, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very degree is divided into 60. minutes, and every minute into 60. ſeconds, and every minute into 60. thirds, and ſo of the reſt following, until ten.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The riſing and ſetting of the Signes.</head>
                  <p>Beſides, you muſt take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, that when we have the lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt day of Summer, which is to ſay, then when the Sun is in the beginning of <hi>Cancer,</hi> there ariſes ſix Signes in a day, which do riſe directly, and in the night ſix
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:121191:71"/>
Signes obliquely; And on the contrary, when we have the ſhorteſt day of the year, to wit, the Sun being in the beginning of <hi>Capricorn,</hi> then ſix Signes riſe in a day obliquely, and the ſix of the night directly; but when the Sun is either in th' one or th' o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Equinoctial point, then they riſe, three Signes directly, and three obliquely in a day, and in the night in like manner: For there is a Rule, that let the day or the night be long or ſhort, as you will, ſix Signes riſe in the day, and ſix by night; ſo that either for the length, or the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the day or night, neither the more, or leſſe Signes do riſe. For the knowledge of which Signes, you muſt take notice of the Characters following, as the Aſtrologers mark them.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:121191:72"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aries</hi> with ſuch a Sign. ♈</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Taurus</hi> ſuch a one. ♉</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gemini</hi> ſuch. ♊</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cancer.</hi> ♋</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Leo.</hi> ♌</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Virgo.</hi> ♍</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Libra.</hi> ♎</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Scorpio.</hi> ♏</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sagitarius.</hi> ♐</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Capricornus.</hi> ♑</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aquarius.</hi> ♒</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Piſces.</hi> ♓</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Let this ſuffice for the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry concerning the 12. Signes, let us come now to the 7. Planets: whereof we ſhould here make a Table or Figure; but becauſe we have ſent the Reader to Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merides, in relation to the Signs, we will do the like concerning the Planets, contenting my ſelf only in this place, to ſet down their Characters, for the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:121191:72"/>
of the more eaſie underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and their differences. Behold then how the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> mark them;
<list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Saturne</hi> thus. ♄</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Iupiter</hi> thus. ♃</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mars</hi> thus. ♂</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Sun</hi> thus. ☉</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Venus</hi> thus. ♀</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Mercury</hi> thus. ☿</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Luna</hi> thus. <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Here followes the difference of the Planets, as well for purging and blooding, as for the making o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther operations upon humane bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Moſt good.</hi> ♃ ♂</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Indifferent.</hi> ☉ <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ☿</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Bad.</hi> ♄ ♂</item>
                  </list>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:121191:73"/>
                  <head>The Chirurgion muſt Encounter the Starrs.</head>
                  <p>And you muſt take notice, that then when <hi>Mercury</hi> is with a good Planet, he augments its goodneſſe, and with a bad one its Malignity: wherefore it is that when one is wounded, you muſt take notice whether <hi>Mercury</hi> be not with ſome bad Planet, which rules the part wounded; and if ſo, then the <hi>Chirurgion</hi> muſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter the Starrs, and ſo you muſt minde theſe things, but moſt eſpecially in blooding; to the end that (we having done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing improperly through our negligence) may have an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of praiſe and thanks-giving, to the Authour of all things: to whom Father, Son, and Spirit, be honour, and glory, for ever, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:121191:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> That it is neceſſary that the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgion have the Aſtronomicall figure in his ſtudy, or in his ſhop; and of the profit that proceeds therefrom, as well for the ſick per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as for thoſe who exerciſe it; which is proved by a Hiſtory, and other examples. As alſo, that it is better to keep &amp; cleanſe the blood then to evacuate it. With the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of two admirable reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, for this end.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The good deſire of the Authour.</head>
                  <p>I Should deſire by good reaſon, as well for the profit of thoſe who ſearch relief or Remedy from <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> as for the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al contentment of thoſe that pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121191:74"/>
it, (to the end that the whole, might be to the hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and glory of God) that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Chirurgion</hi> had within his ſhop, the Aſtronomicall figure, as formerly the Ancients had; and who had recourſe unto it, then when they would know the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a Starr, on the part whereon they were to operate, obſerving with all their power the riſing and ſetting of the above mentioned Signes, and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations; inſomuch that the Antients have not found it to be unprofitable. Of the truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (among ſeverall of them) <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noldus de villa nova,</hi> ſhall be a moſt faithful witneſſe. Therefore I ſhall again heartily intreat the Chirurgions, that they would take heed unto it, and not to pretend that their Art is ſubject to <hi>Calumnie;</hi> ſeeing it is they themſelves, which are the cauſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121191:74"/>
of their arts being ſo Calumnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whilſt they neglect that which is moſt neceſſary to be known in their profeſſion, to wit, <hi>Aſtronomie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ignorance of Aſtronomy is, cauſe of great evils.</head>
                  <p>Inſomuch that not having the knowledge of it, there doth arive many evil Accidents, and the vulgar being ignorant of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them, do Calumniate and ſleight all the Judgments of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions</hi> and their (ſo admirable) Art together. See how it is weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and eſteemed at nought and contemned by the ignorant, and all this by reaſon of the ſmall care which <hi>Chirurgions</hi> have to minde it well. But, to ſhew that the knowledge of the Starrs is moſt neceſſary for a <hi>Chirurgion,</hi> I will inſert a Hiſtory which may
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:121191:75"/>
ſerve as an example to thoſe, who ſhall know well how to put it in practice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Remarkable Hiſtory.</head>
                  <p>It happened that at <hi>Chatelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rault,</hi> a Chirurgion having blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Maid in the right arme, in the time when the Moon paſſed under the ſigne of <hi>Gemini:</hi> on the next day about noon there came upon her a great defluxion cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing inflammation, with a feaver: at the ſame time this Maide goes complaining to another <hi>Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> ſaying, that one had ſpoiled her, &amp; had prickt her Nerve, &amp; that it rendred her a Cripple, uſing revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings concerning him that had blooded her: they appeaſed her as well as they could, promiſing her, it would be nothing, and that ſhe ſhould be ſuddainly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, applying unto her at the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121191:75"/>
ſame inſtant a Cataplaſm, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing Cataplaſm upon Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaſm, and making Revulſion by blooding; but notwithſtanding all they could do, the Arme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came extreamly ſwell'd, yea to the danger of her perſon: inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that in a ſhort time, the ſame was known through the whoſe town, and behold here the Poor <hi>Chirurgion</hi> is ſo diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as not to be ever received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to any houſe upon any occaſion whatſoever, (the preſent age is ſo ſcruplous, being ignorant of things how they may happen). Which he ſeeing, reſolved to frame a rational excuſe to defend his reputation, and to maintain his innocence, which he did when there was a pretty Company to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in the houſe of the ſaid ſick perſon: his reaſons were theſe. That ſhe was upon the point of her Termes, and that her body was
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:121191:76"/>
Cachochymicall and full of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and that at the time when ſhe was blooded, ſhe helpd at the waſhing a Buck, and alſo to do other buſineſs of the houſe, and other things which might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite defluxion and attraction in the part, having been blooded before; for if ſo it had been, ſaid he, that I had prickt the Nerve or Tendon, the Accidents would have appeared in the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, as convulſion, Spaſm, great pain in the part, difficulty in the Action; none of which happen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (ſaith he), one may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by judge, that it was none of my fault.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>In Lunar purgations, the vein of the Arme muſt not be opened.</head>
                  <p>But that is contrary, for his reaſons ſerved to fight againſt himſelf; for ſince ſhe was upon
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121191:76"/>
the point of her purgations, he ought not to have been ſo raſh, as to have opened a vein on her Arme, but rather the <hi>Saphena</hi> for provoking them, and ſeveral other reaſons which rendered him mute, confeſſing as it were by his ſilence, that he was in fault; but if he had known how to have diſcourſed or argued, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſcience of Aſtronomie, he had been heard attentively, in regard that was not vulgar to them. Notwithſtanding, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing to dreſſe the Maide, ſhe was cured in three weeks, but not without having indured a great deal of pain.</p>
                  <p>I have been willing to relate this ſtory, (which happened in the year 1613. in the ſaid <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtelerand</hi> in the ſhop of a Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion named <hi>Bureau,</hi> to the end, I might induce and provoke the Chirurgion to learn the Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121191:77"/>
of the Starrs, with all his power, for otherwiſe it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that he ſhould come to his intended end of <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> Elective; without ſome dangerous accident, which I have ſeen hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſeverall times: but for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity ſake, I ſhall paſſe on.</p>
                  <p>Yet notwithſtanding <hi>Guidon dela Nanche</hi> ſpeaking of blooding in his Tract, <hi>[Dela Santé Corporel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le]</hi> ſaith, that he hath ſeen ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall expert, and famous <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgions</hi> of his time, as well at <hi>Paris</hi> and <hi>Mont-pelliere,</hi> as at o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good Cities of <hi>France,</hi> and at the Court, and Armies-Royall, let blood, which hath cauſed ſwellings in the Armes, and other parts which have been blooded, and many other evil accidents, which (as he ſaith, flattering himſelf) did arive by the fault of the Patient, pulling back or throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his Arme, through fear,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121191:77"/>
or ſudaine apprehenſion, or by having lain upon his Arme after blooding, or by ſleeping, or by having wrought, or exerciſed the Arme. <hi>In the ſecond Tome, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Chap.</hi> 16. He here deceives him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf exceedingly, for if he had ſearched further, he would have found that it is rather the fault of the <hi>Phlebotomiſer,</hi> then the <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomiſed;</hi> for in regard they are ignorant of the concurrence of the Starrs, and of the houre and time wherein they govern the part, they commit theſe block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and irreparable faults.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Objection.</head>
                  <p>This is alſo for anſwer to that which may be objected. That ſeveral ſick perſons are blooded at the ſame time, and yet they are not ill: It may be ſo, but I ſay, that if there happen no <hi>Malady</hi> in the part touched with the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121191:78"/>
Lancet, yet there happens other <hi>Symptomes,</hi> as vomitting, weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vertigo, Giddy-headed, ſouning, nocturnall paines, and ſometimes death.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Accidents ariving in blooding, through ignorance of the Starrs.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Objection.</head>
                  <p>But (may ſome ſay) that is by reaſon of the great evacuation of blood. To that I anſwer, that experience lets us ſee every day, that when there hath not been drawn out, perhaps an half ounce of blood from the patient, that he falls into ſome one of theſe accidents.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Objection.</head>
                  <p>Yes (but will ſome reply) that
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121191:78"/>
is becauſe he hath conceited ſuch a thing but who hath ever heard ſay that, that which one hath premeditated, (it may be a day or two before) is capable to do us hurt, when we come to effect it? It cannot be in anywiſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us leave all theſe Trifles, and let us follow verity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Objection.</head>
                  <p>But (will ſome one reply) the knowledge of the Starrs with the obſervation of them, is prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited?</p>
                  <p>To that I anſwer, That in truth if one ſhould beleeve that the Starrs had Soveraigne power over men, he would be worthy of Cenſure: but we do not find in any place, that any perſon hath ever been blamed, for knowing and obſerving the elevation of the Starrs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:121191:79"/>
                  <head>Advertiſment of the Authour.</head>
                  <p>For Concluſion, I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent my ſelf, to admoniſh the <hi>Chirurgion Phlebotomiſt,</hi> to behave himſelf wiſely, with reaſon, in the extraction of blood, for it is the treaſure of life; inſomuch that you had better conſerve and cleanſe the blood, then to evacuate it inconſiderably; in regard that doth ſhorten our daies, and is the cauſe of ſeverall other Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, as we have ſaid elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
                  <p>But, will ſome ſay, By what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would you make uſe of the extraction of blood, [in the time of neceſſity,] as when a man falls from on high, in great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuſions of the interiour and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour parts; or when one hath received ſome dry blow, or in the <hi>Pluriſie,</hi> and other <hi>Maladies,</hi> whereof you diſcourſe, in your [time of neceſſity.] To that I
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121191:79"/>
anſwer, that it is true, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it, for three cauſes, which induce me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of it, in that manner. The firſt is the honour and reſpect which I bear to the <hi>Hippocratique</hi> Doctrine, and that of <hi>Galen,</hi> for having been nouriſhed therein, ever ſince my young years.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, becauſe by that meanes, I would give to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, (as I ſhall ſhew in a book which I will make apart from this) the agreeing reaſon and affimity, that there is between the books of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Galen,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> as I have made one Chapter thereof in my <hi>[Petite Chirurgie Chymique.]</hi> The third reaſon is, That ſo the Learned <hi>Chirurgion</hi> may make uſe of it, as he ſhall know to be neceſſary; for ſince in all his operations, he ought to follow Nature, he ought alſo
<pb n="411" facs="tcp:121191:80"/>
to take ſpeciall heed to maintain and preſerve Her, and not to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her, as he doth in the emiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of blood, which is the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Life, as before I have ſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Definition of the Pleuriſy.</head>
                  <p>For, I pray, how can it be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the blood, which is out of its veſſells ſpilt, in capacity of certain parts of the body, yea even Clotted and Coagulated therein, can re-enter into the veſſell to be evacuated by blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for example, in the <hi>Pleuriſy</hi> which is a tumour made of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile blood which comes out of the veine <hi>Azuges,</hi> ſtopt between the <hi>Membrana pleura,</hi> and the Muſcels <hi>Meſopluri;</hi> in the curing whereof they preſcribe <hi>Blooding, Gliſters, Syrops, Tablets,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like remedies. But I aske
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:121191:80"/>
what is it that blooding ſerves for there? ſeeing that the blood (which as we have ſaid is out of the veines) cannot enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into again, to be thereby evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; I know well, that they will anſwer me, that the matter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in the ſame place, doth not enter into the veines to be evacuated; but that they uſe it for the hindering of any more, from flowing into that place; and alſo that the Medicaments given inwardly, do work more eaſily. Oh this is a pritty do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for the healing of a pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent! to weaken nature, (which one ought rather to corroborate) for the rendring her more ſtrong; to ſtrive againſt the diſeaſe, for curing the <hi>Pleuriſy,</hi> they evacuate the good and pure blood, which ought to be preſerved for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the ſtrength of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and leave the impure blood
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:121191:81"/>
in the body, which ought to be taken away.</p>
                  <p>I will not therefore ſay, that blooding being performed in the beginning of the true <hi>Pleuriſie,</hi> is not profitable, but is very ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary being performed oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely: but (oh unfortunate time!) I have ſeen thoſe who in all the ſeaſons of that <hi>Malady,</hi> do not forbear with too bold a raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to evacuate this Treaſure of the life.</p>
                  <p>But, to the end that none may continue any longer in this er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and that I may not amuſe my ſelf by diſputing in theſe things, therein following <hi>Galen,</hi> who is not willing that one ſhould diſpute neither of <hi>Apollo,</hi> nor of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> but that one ſhould endeavour to inlarge the Doctrine, for I know that one may alleadg Sophiſticall Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prove falſities, but it
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:121191:81"/>
muſt be to thoſe who know not how to guard themſelves from them; I ſhall onely ſay that <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> underſtood well what he ſaid, when he affirmed, that by probable and ſubtile fictions in Phyſick, there did often hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen great and heavy falls. From whence one may perceive that Phyſick is fallen ſo miſerably, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been called (by its own props or upholders) opinionate, or ſubject to opinion, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecturall. (616. <hi>Praecept. Com.</hi> 2 <hi>Aph.</hi> 2. <hi>de Comp. me Secund. loc.</hi>) That the verity thereof cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare but by ſubtile Arguments, and that is is incertain. This is it which hath induced <hi>Galen</hi> to reprehend <hi>Hippocrates</hi> for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving called Phyſick Conjectural, which he had need to do, ſeeing it is neither Conjecturall, nor imaginary, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Scientifique.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:121191:82"/>So that as a kingdom divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelf, cannot ſtand, can Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick ſubſiſt when the ſupports ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are divided among themſelves? That is it which hath given occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulgar,</hi> to ſlight it, as it is ſlighted. But wherefore do we aſſemble ſeven or eight, as well Phyſicians as Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for conſultation upon one diſeaſe, which if it be known, what need is there of opinion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it?</p>
                  <p>In ſhort, either the Science of Phyſick is True, or it is not True. If it be true, its rules are certain. But it is true, that it is true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is of Gods Creation, and God and nature make nothing vain: It follows then, that its precepts are true. Which <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> perceived, although he was an <hi>Ethnique,</hi> in regard he ſaith, the Philoſophicall Phyſician is like unto God; but he cannot
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:121191:82"/>
be ſo, who follows not Truth. That is it which I deſire to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, avoiding, to the beſt of my power, <hi>Sophistryes,</hi> which are the onely cauſes of nouriſhing fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, wherewith (to my great trouble) our Chirurgery is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed. But to the end, as I have ſaid before, I may not keep the Reader in ſuch an errour, I give him two Remedies, for all ſorts of Contuſions, Dry-blowes, Bruiſes, Phlegmatick-Swelling, blood clotted, or congeled with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the body, by reaſon of a fall from ſome high place, In which, from theſe two Remedies bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> one ſhall ſee a very great effect, without running to <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> as many who follow the ordinary errour do. One may by theſe ſerve him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to his own great honour, the benefit of the Patient, and to the Glory of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:121191:83"/>Of theſe two <hi>Medicines,</hi> the one you may take inwardly, when you ſuſpect there is ſome quantity of blood ſpilt and coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated in the inner parts of the body; and the other is to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed outwardly, when the Phleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick Tumor appears to the ſenſe of the eye; and both of them together may ſerve, as in <hi>Pleuriſie, Eſhimoſe,</hi> (collection of Corrupt matter, within the body, between Breaſt and Lungs) <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyeme,</hi> and ſuch like, as I intend to mention in the book which I have heretofore promiſed, by the aſſiſtance of God.</p>
                  <p>Let us come now to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of theſe two Remedies, which are as followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Remedy for the externall Parts.</head>
                  <p>℞. Flowers of white <hi>Mullein</hi> M.j.
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:121191:83"/>
flowers of St. <hi>Iohns-Wort</hi> M. iij. roote of <hi>Aſclepias</hi> or <hi>Swallow-wort</hi> M. <hi>ſs. Mumie</hi> ℥ j. freſh oyle Olive <hi>Lib.</hi> ij. <hi>There bentine al. Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine Lib.</hi> j. <hi>White-wine Lib.</hi> iij. which you muſt boyle together on a ſoft fire, for the ſpace of five houres, then you muſt afterwards put it into a Glaſſe well ſtopt, and ſet it in the Sun, leave it there for the ſpace of a Month or ſix weeks; then you muſt ſtrain the whole through a peece of Cloath, and Squeze well the dregs; &amp; you ſhall have an oyle, incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the effect above mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which you muſt keep care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and therewith anoynt the part, evening and morning.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:121191:84"/>
                  <head>A proper Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall parts.</head>
                  <p>Rec. of good <hi>Rubarbe,</hi> ℥ ij. <hi>Mumie,</hi> ℥ ſs. <hi>Red Gum, Lack, Sperma Caeti,</hi> ℥ j. <hi>Bolarmeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack,</hi> and <hi>Terra Sigillata,</hi> an ℥ ſs. root of <hi>Aſclepias</hi> ℥ iij. you muſt beat them all to powder, of which you muſt give the weight of a drag. with the water <hi>Florum Tiliae, Tilia</hi> is a tree bearing fruit as great as a bean, round &amp; in which are ſeeds like to Aniceſeeds, ſome call it the <hi>Linden</hi> tree, or the like, for it is moſt good to take away the Phlegmatick tumour, as well within the body as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. There is no neceſſity of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:121191:84"/>
diſcovering any other of theſe <hi>Medicines,</hi> now, becauſe it is not my intent in this place, for I have not brought in theſe two in this place, but onely to ſhew that one may cure theſe kinds of <hi>Maladies,</hi> and ſeverall others, without having recourſe to <hi>Phle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>botomy,</hi> of which <hi>Medicines</hi> the Learned <hi>Chirurgion</hi> will know how to make uſe according as he ſhall ſee occaſion; and will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent others, according as neceſſity ſhall require. But above all, I intreat thoſe who ſhall read this little treatiſe, that they will not ſleight it: for I have not taken pen in hand, to Teach; but to give wholeſome advice and Councell for the ſick, and moſt neceſſary for the augmentation of the honour, (which the true <hi>Chirurgions</hi> aſpire unto) and which is more, to provoke to
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:121191:85"/>
do better, as I have ſaid elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where; to the end, that doing and perſuing from good to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we may go into heaven with God: to whom Father, Son, and holy Spirit, be honour and glory, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:121191:85"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of <hi>Veins</hi> to be blooded for ſeveral Infirmities which come upon mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; alſo of the uſe and benefit of <hi>Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-glaſſes,</hi> with ſcarrification, and without ſcarrifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; what muſt be obſerved in that Operation; &amp; laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of <hi>Horſleeches.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough it is true, I have with good reaſon here before
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:121191:86"/>
ſaid, that it is not needful to blood for all maladies, and at random without any conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as is done ordinarily: yet I ſhall not omit to deſcribe the number of the veins, proper to be blooded, with the benefit of opening them: together, with the uſe of Cuping-glaſſes and Horſleeches; for I ſhall thereby pleaſe the <hi>Galienists</hi> and <hi>Paracel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians;</hi> and it is alſo the end which I have reſpected.</p>
               <p>Let us begin then at the Vein, in the middle of the fore-head, which is between the two eye-browes, uſually called <hi>Recta, ſive preparata,</hi> the breathing of that vein is good againſt old Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for foul Ulcers, Leproſie, ſcabbineſs, Morphew, Inpetigine, in Maladies of the eyes, in old continuing pains of the head, in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:121191:86"/>
the affections of the brain, in madneſs or raging.</p>
               <p>The two veins of the Temples, are proper to be breathed in the Megrim, in the great pain of the head, in continuing maladies, old Inflammation of the upper skin of the eye (call'd Ophthalmy) in cloudy dulneſs of minde, watring of the Eyes, Pimples, or Scabs on the Eye-lid.</p>
               <p>The veins of the little corners of the Eyes, which makes a little extuberance upon the <hi>Os Jugale,</hi> are to be blooded againſt the ſame Maladies, as thoſe of the Temples.</p>
               <p>The veins behinde, or round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the eares, which appear in the hollow place, behinde them in the place, where (if you put
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:121191:87"/>
your finger, you will feel pulſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is to be breathed, for the Megrim, old Cathars, the ſcald, for reviving or repairing the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory; for Ulcers of the Eares or Neck, for clearing or mundifying the countenance, for the pain and defluxion in the teeth, for the pains, and ripe impoſthumes and Ulcers of the Head.</p>
               <p>The Vein which is between the two Cartilages of the Noſe, for the Phrenſie, in acute Feavers, old pains of the Head, the old redneſs of the Face, for the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of bleared Eyes running with water; for dulneſs or heavineſs in the Head, for Hemorrhoides, the itching, or tickling of the Noſe, and Apoſthumes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>The veins under the Tongue, which are called <hi>Ranulles,</hi> for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthumes of the Throat, and the mouth, for the Squinacy, (you
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:121191:87"/>
muſt firſt blood the Cephalique) for the heavineſs of the tongue, for the Apoplexie, and for all pains of the teeth, for the pain and malady of the gums, for Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thars, and other defluxions of the Head, for the Cough, for the ſpots of the face, and in the paſſions of the Jawes.</p>
               <p>The vein, which is between the Chin and the under lip, for the ſtinking of ones mouth, for the corroding, breaking out, and for chapt lips, or ſoreneſs of the gums, for Ulcers of the Noſe, for an ill complexioned face, for the pains of the Dugs, or Paps, and for the pain of the Head.</p>
               <p>The two veins of the neck, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Jugulary</hi> Veins, th' one on the right ſide, and th' other on the left, for the Impetigo, or Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worm, for <hi>Serpigo</hi> being Puſhes, and angry read wheals, the <hi>Noli me tangere;</hi> for the <hi>Cancer Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive,</hi>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:121191:88"/>
in the ſwelling of the Gums for the <hi>Squinacy,</hi> for the <hi>Asthma,</hi> for a hoarſe voyce, for the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humes of the Lungs, for the Paſſion of the Spleen, for the pain of the ſides.</p>
               <p>The Cephalique Vein which they call humerall, Cubitall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the thumb and the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finger, one may make inciſion of it, without any danger in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior part of it, in the bending of the Arm, againſt the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Stomach, and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the hand.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Median,</hi> in the bending of the Arm, between the <hi>Cephalique,</hi> and the <hi>Baſilique,</hi> which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called black, and the vein of the heart; and this is for the evacation of all the humours, in maladies of the whole body, principally thoſe of the heart, and ſtrengthens the ſtomach, or appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, for all the Paſſions of the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:121191:88"/>
ſtomach, of the Liver, of the Spleen, of the Lungs, of the Breaſt, and of all the Body.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Baſilique,</hi> called the great <hi>Baſilique</hi> of the Liver, for the Spleen, the Breaſt, the Lungs, the Stomach, the Liver, abundance of Choler, and for the heat of the Liver, for the pain of the Teeth, of the Back, of the ſides, <hi>partes laterales,</hi> and of all the members, for the Hemorrhogie of the Noſe, for the itching and pricking in the skin, and in Feavers.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Salvatella,</hi> called the <hi>Sple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natique</hi> vein, between the <hi>Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular,</hi> or little finger, and the <hi>Medicus</hi> (otherwiſe called the Ring-finger) declining towards it; the breathing of that vein, to wit, that on the right hand, is prevalent in the affections, and obſtructions of the Liver, and that of the left hand, in the ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings of the Spleen; in ſhort, the
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:121191:89"/>
one or the other, is prevalent for the pain or the Heart, Yellow Jaundice to all Feavers, to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in the breaſt, for the yellowneſs comming in the eyes.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Apoplectique,</hi> or <hi>vena po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitis,</hi> which is at the bending of the knee, for the provocation of the <hi>Menſtrue,</hi> for pains in Arms, for affections in the Loynes, for the provocation of Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoides for pains in the Blather, for paſſions in the teſticles, for the infirmity of the feet, for all mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Articulations.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Iſchiadique,</hi> or <hi>Sciatique</hi> Vein, under the Vein which runs acroſſe the outward Ancle of the Foot, calld <hi>Maleolla,</hi> or round about it; for the pains of the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium,</hi> or hip-Gout, the Foot-Gout, Leproſie, <hi>Varices</hi> or Veins ſweld with corrupted blood, for pains in the Bladder, for the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:121191:89"/>
of Urine, for Ulcers and ſwellings of the Teſticles, in Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Tumors of the Kidneys, and other evils.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Saphaena,</hi> under the <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Maleolla,</hi> or Ancle, vein of the Foot; yea, which runs a croſſe it ſometimes; for all the paſſions of the Matrix, for all the affections of the Teſticles, old ſcabbineſs, ſalt Phlegme, for the griefs of the <hi>Cox. &amp; tibia,</hi> It ſtrongly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vokes the <hi>Menſtrue</hi> and the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhoides;</hi> for the purging of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terus,</hi> after birth of a Childe; it takes away barrenneſs; for the affections of the yard, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rivation of blood from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, Yard, and Teſticles.</p>
               <p>The <hi>vena Tarſi,</hi> appearing and ending about the great Toes, for the vices of the Bladder, to the faults or ſpots of the Face, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation of the upper skin of the Eye, call'd <hi>Ophthalmia;</hi> for
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:121191:90"/>
redneſs of the Eyes, blear-eyed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, running with water, being red and ſoare; for the <hi>Cancer,</hi> for the <hi>Varices</hi> of the <hi>Tibia,</hi> with corrupt matter, and for the mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies near the <hi>Saphena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Vein in the middle of the Foot, is to be blooded for pains, or maladies in the Kidneys; for the wearineſs, and dull heavineſs of the Members of the Body; Apoplexie, Palſie, and Epilepſie.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:121191:90"/>
                  <head>Of <hi>Cupping-glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and of the benefit of the uſe of them in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</head>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Intentions for which one ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi>Cupping-glaſſes.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Every one knoweth well, what <hi>Cupping-glaſſes</hi> are.</p>
                     <p>They are to be applyed, where blooding cannot well be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed; ſome are with ſcarrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and others without it; thoſe with ſcartification, are for the evacuation of a matter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junct in one part; and the other is, to make attraction; they are
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:121191:91"/>
alſo applyed to make revulſion and derivation in ſeveral parts; as for deflexion into the Eyes, the <hi>Cupping-glaſſes</hi> are to be applyed upon the ſhoulders; for the flux of the blood at the Noſe they are to be applyed to the <hi>Hypocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dryes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Beſides, they being applyed without ſcarrification, are good for diverting of Apoſthumes from the Noble parts, to the ignoble parts; and to draw the heat to a member debilitated by cold.</p>
                     <p>They are to be uſed in the Cholique, being applyed above the Navel, or under it, for eaſing of the pain, for drawing from the Center to the Circumference.</p>
                     <p>To evacuate the windineſs, to ſtop the Hemorrhoides, to reduce the members into their place.</p>
                     <p>For the pain of the Matrix they being put upon the Navel, the part being firſt well warmed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="137" facs="tcp:121191:91"/>For the immoderate Flux of the <hi>Menſtrue,</hi> if they be applyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Region of the Paps, at the ſame time.</p>
                     <p>Alſo for the Flux or bleeding at Noſe, (as we have ſaid already) being applyed upon the Liver, if it be the right Noſtril that bleeds; and if it be the left Noſtril that bleedes, you muſt apply them to the Region of the Spleen.</p>
                     <p>For drawing peſtiferous A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthumes from the Interior parts, and in <hi>venerious Bubons.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For diverting the blood which flowes immoderately to one place.</p>
                     <p>To ſtop the Fluxes of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.</p>
                     <p>For the drawing out of Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and for the coldneſs of the <hi>Ventricle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But in the uſe of them, you muſt conſider four things.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, the matter of them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="138" facs="tcp:121191:92"/>Secondly, The manner of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying them.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, The time.</p>
                     <p>And Fourthly, The Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and parts to be applyed to.</p>
                     <p>In the matter, you muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der three things.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, The ſubſtance, which is either of Horn, or of Glaſſe, or Metal, or Earth.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, The quantity of them, which is great, mean, or little.</p>
                     <p>And Thirdly, The Figure or Form, which is Circular, or round, and ſomewhat long, like a Horn.</p>
                     <p>The manner of applying them, is with fire, or elſe without fire, and that with ſcarrifications, or without ſcarrifications, (as we have ſaid) deep or ſuperficial.</p>
                     <p>The time of the Application, is either neceſſary, (which being) there is nothing to be reſpected,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:121191:92"/>
or Elective, and then you muſt take heed, that it be with the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary regularity propoſed by <hi>Guidon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Concerning the intentions we have ſpoken enough thereof al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready before.</p>
                     <p>Notwithſtanding, you muſt take notice, that the Attraction of <hi>Cupping-glaſſes,</hi> doth not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon any natural faculties of them, nor of any ſimilitude, but upon an accidental vertue of hindering of the Vacuum.</p>
                     <p>This Attraction is made, when the fire for want of ventilation, or breathing, (being choaked) doth degenerate into Ayr, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth leſſe room then when it was fire; for, as the Philoſophers ſay, one little part of Ayr, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth ten parts of fire; and on the contrary, ten parts of fire turn themſelves into one part of ayr; ſo that nature to ſupply the place
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:121191:93"/>
of the fire, contracts the fleſh, the Spirits, and the humours into its place.</p>
                     <p>Finally, the parts whereupon the <hi>Cupping-glaſſes</hi> are to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, are the ſhoulders, the neck, the hinder part of the Head, the Hypocondyres, the Reins of the back, the ſtomack, the Matrix, the Thighes, the Buttocks; for the better underſtanding whereof, we will mention them more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, and diſtinctly, together, with the maladies wherein they are profitable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>Of the uſe of <hi>Cupping-glaſſes,</hi> as to the parts or places, as well with ſcarrification, as without it.</head>
                     <p>In the firſt place, <hi>Cupping-glaſſes</hi> being applyed upon the Head, are very commodious in madneſs or diſtraction, <hi>ſcotomie canicie,</hi> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineſs, ſcabbineſs, knots or pim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the eyes, and in the mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:121191:93"/>
of the nape of the neck; but they do prejudice the Intellect, and the memory, becauſe they do ſtupifie.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed to the forehead, do help very much in the pain of the hinder part of the head, in the heavineſs and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling thereof, in all affections of the brain, for madneſs and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction; for old infirmities of the face, Ring-worm or Tetter, Ulcers, Leproſie, ſcabbineſs and Morphew, for all the maladies of the Eyes, and for the Vertigo, or ſwimming in the Head; but they do prejudice the reaſon and Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed to the Chyne, are very profitable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Puſtules, and ſwellings in the mouth, for maladies of the Teeth and Gums, for the Spots and viciouſneſs of the face, for Wens, for ſwellings in the throat,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:121191:94"/>
for all maladies of the Jawes.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed between the neck and ſhoulders, are very commodious for maladies of the face, of the neck, Teeth, noſtrils, eyes, for the ſtinking ſmell of the mouth, for Ring-worms or Tet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for the Squinacy, having firſt opened the Cephalique, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian vein, but they do prejudice the memory, and cauſe the head to ſhake.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed between the ſhoulders, in the part againſt the heart and ſtomack, are very commodious in the affections of the Breaſt, in the maladies of the neck, for the Aſthma or Spaſme, for the trembling or quivering of the heart, and for the blood in the throat; but they do preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the ſtomack and the heart: the which in its trembling, doth not ſend forth the blood.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="143" facs="tcp:121191:94"/>They, are to be applyed upon the breaſt in the pain thereof, and for the Asthma, on the Region of the Liver, for the Inflammation thereof, upon the back, for the pains that happen therein, over againſt the part grieved.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed upon the ſtomack they avail much in ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings thereof; and when it is grown cold, and for the humours and viciouſneſs thereof.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed upon the hands, are prevalent againſt all the diſtempers of the Head, Eyes and Eares.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed upon the Reyns, are prevalent againſt the Apotemes of the Coccix, Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine, ſo Hemorrhoides, Gout, Leproſie, for the itching of the back, and ſcabbineſs there; for the windineſs and coldneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and other diſtempers for the windes in the Bladder.</p>
                     <p>
                        <pb n="144" facs="tcp:121191:95"/>They being applyed upon the Navel, are prevalent againſt the Maladies of the Matrix, and for the Cholick.</p>
                     <p>Upon the Hypocondries, to draw back the Impetuous iſſuing of blood at the Noſtrils, and for immoderate Flux of blood from the Uterus.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed to the Loynes, ſtop the Hemorrhoides, and cauſe the pain of the back to ceaſe; as alſo of the Matrix, and of the Loynes, to repreſs the too ſtrong deſire of Venery, to heal the ſcabbineſs and Apoſthumes within ſide of the Thighes.</p>
                     <p>They being applyed upon the Buttocks, do cleanſe the blood, and are beneficial for the cure of the white Menſtrue, for the pains of the privities, and of the Loynes and the Breaſt.</p>
                     <p>In the Interior part of the Coccyx, for the Apoſthumes of
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:121191:95"/>
the Teſticles, in the Iſſues, or ſores of the ſides, and of the Coccyx.</p>
                     <p>They are to be applied on the hinder part of the Coccyx, in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthemes, and running ſores of the Buttocks.</p>
                     <p>They are to be applied under the Ham, or bending of the knee, for the pulſation of the ſinew, near the knee, which turns the Legg inwards, which is occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a cold humour, and for Ulcers and running ſores of the Feet.</p>
                     <p>They being applied to the fleſhy parts of the Thighes, they do good to all the parts of the Body; for the Tumors, or ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of the Buttocks, and for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſthemes thereof; for pains of the Reins of the back, and the Bladder; for Fluxions in the Eyes, for affections in the Head, for cold Apoſthemes, and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:121191:96"/>
of the knees, for maladies of the ſtomack, or breaſt, pains of the back, for Apoſthemes of the Teſticles, for wounds and ulcers in the Coccyx, and in the privy parts; yea, in the old pains of the Matrix, for purging the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix of its ſuperfluities, for the Apoſthemes and ſores of the hands, to provoke the Hemor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhoides, and the Menſtrue; for the Sciatica, Gout, and Vertigo, or ſwimming in the Head.</p>
                     <p>I ſhould have ſpoken much more of the utility of <hi>Cupping-glaſſes;</hi> but I forbear for brevity ſake. And come now to ſpeak of obſervation concerning the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the uſe of them.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:121191:96"/>
                  <head>Thoſe things which ought to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, before applying of Cup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping-glaſſes.</head>
                  <p>THoſe who are beſt verſed in the Rules and Obſervations, Aſtrological and Medicinal, are of opinion, that you ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie <hi>Cupping-glaſſes,</hi> or little Horns, for that purpoſe, upon Phlegmatique perſons, when the Moon is in <hi>Aries,</hi> or <hi>Sagittarius.</hi> To the Cholerique, when ſhe is in <hi>Cancer, Scorpio,</hi> or <hi>Piſces.</hi> To the melancholique, when the Moon is found in <hi>Gemini, Libra,</hi>
                     <pb n="148" facs="tcp:121191:97"/>
or <hi>Aquarius:</hi> notwithſtanding, you muſt take notice, not to ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie the part, when the Moon is in the Sign which governs it, and in generall, not to uſe it, neither with Glaſſes, nor with little Horns, when the Moon is in <hi>Leo:</hi> it is true, there are Horns applied at all times, but it is without Fire or Candle.</p>
                  <p>You muſt alſo take notice, not to ſcarrifie before four years of age, nor after 60. And you muſt alſo avoid that operation, in the new and full Moon.</p>
                  <p>The ſcarrifications may be made about the ſecond or third houre of the day, an houre before eating or drinking.</p>
                  <p>The place where one ought to applie the <hi>Cupping-glaſſes,</hi> or <hi>Horns,</hi> ſhould be well fomented with warm water, or uſe frictions for half an houre, or an hour, with a warm Linnen Cloth; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:121191:97"/>
to ſuch who you ſuppoſe have thick blood; or, if it be in the winter time.</p>
                  <p>Beſides, you muſt not apply them, before the Body be empri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or purged; neither are they proper in a Plethorique body, nor in any part affected with a Phlegmon; as for the reſt, the wiſe Chirurgion will diſpenſe with theſe rules, according to the violence of the Maladie. Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty derogating from all Lawes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Here followeth the uſe of <hi>Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeches.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>There is no ſo dull block-head, but knowes what <hi>Horſleeches</hi> are; they are ordinarily applied there
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:121191:98"/>
where <hi>Cupping-glaſſes</hi> can take no place, as on the noſe, upon the lips, gums, fingers, privities, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhoides, at the entrance of the <hi>Os Matricis</hi> and other places. One ſhould chooſe them, ſuch as are bred in good clear and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning waters, which have yellow ſtreaks upon their backs, and not thoſe among ruſhes, in bad wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and which are of a horrible colour, and have a great head, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe are venomous. <hi>Gui. Treatiſe</hi> 7. <hi>Section</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. And you muſt not applie them, being freſh taken, but keep them a whole day in clean water; to the end, they may vomit forth that which they have in their Bellies. <hi>Oribas. Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Chap.</hi> 15. It is good to leave them without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, three or four houres ſpace, before you apply them; for they will, after that, be more greedy. You muſt waſh the place, where
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:121191:98"/>
you applie them, with warm water, and then dry, and rub the place with a Linnen Cloth, until it be red, (except in places where there is great pain); then having made a ſlight ſcarrification upon every place, where you would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie the Horſleech, put thereupon a little drop of a Chickens blood, and then applie the Horſleech, holding it in a clean Linnen Cloth; for moſt commonly, they will not take hold, if you hold them in your naked hands; and when they have ſuckt enough, they will fall off themſelves; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, every one knowes the way to make them, and to order them in theſe things. Above all, let one take heed, not to applie them, when the Moon is in the Signe, governing the part; for you muſt obſerve the ſame, in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying theſe, as in the operation
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:121191:99"/>
of blooding, and uſing <hi>Cupping-glaſſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I beſeech the Authour of all things, that all thoſe who read this Treatiſe, may make uſe of it, to their advantage: To whom, Father, Son, and holy Spirit, be honour, and glory, for ever, Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>
               <hi>The end of the Treatiſe of</hi> Phlebotomie.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="153" facs="tcp:121191:99"/>
            <head>A Brief <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> Or, diſcourſe concerning <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi>'s. Wherein is ſhewn how people do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves, in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon them, being ignorant of the Motion of the Starrs.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>All things have a regular motion.</head>
               <p>GOd the Creator, according to his ineſtimable goodneſs, Clemency, and wiſdome put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the nature of things, well or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and regulated motions; inſomuch that he hath been pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:121191:100"/>
that not any thing ſhould move by chance, or raſhly, but that all ſhould move by good or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and a continuall ſucceſſion; And ſo the Starrs, The Elements, the Ocean, the ſeaſons of the year, and the Spheres of the heavens have their motions and viciſſitudes, and performe their Courſes abſolutely regular.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The humors have a Limited courſe.</head>
               <p>In like manner, the humors which are in humane bodies have their effects, their proper moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and certain <hi>Periods;</hi> ſo that in every one of the four Seaſons of the year, each humour per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes its part, and doth exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe its power and faculties upon the body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:121191:100"/>
               <head>Diviſion of the Sun in its Circular Motion.</head>
               <p>So alſo as the Circular motion of the Sun is divided into four parts, which are called Quarters of the Heaven, repreſenting the four Elements and Seaſons of the Year, together with the four parts of the Day; from whence re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teth that there is a certain <hi>Sympathy</hi> as well between the four quarters of the Moon, and the Elements, and the four Seaſons, and the four Humours, and the four parts of the Day; yea I ſhall alſo ſay with the very four Windes, and four Ages; Nay ſuch a <hi>Sympathy,</hi> that it is impoſſible, that (the one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing depraved) the other with which it doth <hi>Sympathize,</hi> ſhould not have a reſentment thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:121191:101"/>
               <head>Diviſion of the Seaſone with the Elements.</head>
               <p>But for the more clear under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding hereof we ſay, That theſe four quarters of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens do repreſent the four Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the four ſeaſons of the year, That is to ſay from the Sun riſing unto the Mid-day, The firſt; from Noon to the Sun ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, The ſecond; from Sun-ſet to midnight, The third; and from thence to Sun riſing, The fourth: ſo that the Sun being in the firſt quadrature with the fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Starrs therein, Then is the ſpring which is repreſented by the Ayre; being in the ſecond, then is the Summer, which is repreſented by the Heavens or Fire; and being in the third cauſeth <hi>Autumn,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented by the Earth; and laſtly being in the fourth, it cauſeth
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:121191:101"/>
Winter, which is repreſented by the water. Moreover we ſee the <hi>Symbolization</hi> of the ſpring, to the Ayre, to blood and to youth; of the Summer, to fire, Choller, and manhood; of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn,</hi> to the Earth, to Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly, and by conſequence the firſt part of old age; and in fine, the fourth is of the Winter, to water, <hi>Phlegme,</hi> and decrepit age.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Diviſion of the day for the Elements and humors of the body.</head>
               <p>The ſame diviſion is of the time wherein the Sun moves round the Earth, which is one day di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into four parts. The firſt part is from three of the Clock in the morning untill Nine; for the Ayre, the ſpring and the blood. And from Nine a Clock in the morning untill three afternoon;
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:121191:102"/>
for the Fire, Summer, and Choler. And from that time untill Nine, for the Earth for <hi>Autumne,</hi> and for Melancho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly: and from thence following, untill three of the morning, for the Water for Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and for <hi>Phlegme.</hi> And if it ſo happen, that one of thoſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be depraved or Malignant in a man, or that thereby a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of its temper or degree, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſallibly it will diſcover it ſelf in the time ſo appropriate or ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Maladies</hi> occaſioned by the Signes, are healed by the oppoſing of contrary Signes.</head>
               <p>Now it is impoſſible that theſe humours <hi>Symbolizing</hi> thus with the Heavens, and the Elements, can continue without alteration; ſeeing that the Starrs do make known their effects in them, as
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:121191:102"/>
we have ſaid in another place: wherefore it is, that the blood hath ſuch force and power, that the Spring being come, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in vigour, doth ingender <hi>Maladies</hi> and feavers of its na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to wit, continuall ones which give no ſpace or reſpite, which <hi>Maladies</hi> are cauſed by the depravation of the three ſignes, which govern the above menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned humour, ſuch are <hi>Gemini Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra</hi> and <hi>Aquarius:</hi> and the healing of ſuch <hi>Maladies,</hi> ought to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in contrary ſignes, which are <hi>Taurus, Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Capricornus.</hi> In like manner, the Choller in Summer, making its courſe and recourſe by daies alternate, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions the <hi>Tertian</hi> feaver, and that by the depravation of the three ſignes, which have influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon that humour; that is to ſay, <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Sagittari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us:</hi> which <hi>Maladies</hi> are cured by
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:121191:103"/>
oppoſition of the contrary ſign as <hi>Cancer, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards the <hi>Phlegme</hi> in Winter, when it is putrify'd, engenders the <hi>Quotidian</hi> intermittent feaver, alſo caus'd by the three ſigns w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> govern that humour, ſuch are <hi>Cancer, Scorpio,</hi> and <hi>Piſces:</hi> and thoſe diſeaſes are cured in like manner, as the laſt above men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and that is, by the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Aries, Leo,</hi> and <hi>Sagitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius:</hi> finally the Melancholly at the beginning of <hi>Autumn</hi> ſtirrs up the quartain Feaver or Ague, cauſed alſo by the aſpect of theſe ſignes which govern over that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, ſuch are <hi>Taurus, Virgo,</hi> and <hi>Capricornus,</hi> and the curing of them is found by the Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of theſe three, <hi>Gemini, Libra,</hi> and <hi>Aquarius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:121191:103"/>
               <head>Wherein conſiſteth the one-day Feaver.</head>
               <p>So the <hi>Ephemere,</hi> or one-day ague, doth end in one day or ſhortly after, in regard that it doth not conſiſt in the Putrefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the humours, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in an inflamed exhaled ſpirit. All which things are done by the ſame reaſon, the ſame proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the ſame order, as the riſing and ſetting of the Sun, The Ebbing and flowing of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and the pleaſant viciſſitude of Plants, and Hearbs, and Trees, which bear ſeed and fruit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How the fits of the Feaver appear.</head>
               <p>Inſomuch that if one do take good heed hereunto, we ſhall eaſily obſerve, that almoſt at the ſame time that the humours are
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:121191:104"/>
forced by the Starrs, they demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the fit of the feaver, not as ſome would ſay, who alleadge that then (when the humors do every one by its turn perform its office) comes the fit of the feaver, but when the time is complea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of each the hours which ſerve to the humors, (provided that they be pure, and not intermingled th' one with th'other) then they ceaſe and conclude.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A Conſiderable reaſon.</head>
               <p>But I ſay, theſe reaſons are not to be received; but, much more to the purpoſe, and with more verity, this; that the acceſſes of the feaver appear then, when the Star which governs the humour concurrs upon it: wherefore it is, that we ſee the fits to become retrograde, or to skipp forward, even as that Star renders it ſelf Retrogade or direct.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:121191:104"/>So that we ought by good right to conſider more narrowly of the Judgment upon <hi>Maladies,</hi> that deſtroyer of that Little World, Man, who is conſtrained to ſuffer Change every four daies, which the Vulgar do call <hi>Criſis,</hi> which is done by looſeneſſe in the belly, by bleeding, vomiting, or ſweat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, excited and occaſioned by the Courſe of the Moon, through the points of the <hi>Zodiac.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But becauſe I have reſolved to ſpeak ſuccinctly of <hi>Criſis</hi>'es in this place, and how you ought to obſerve the Criticall daies, from the Concurrence of the Starrs; we will diſcover firſt what a <hi>Criſis</hi> is; for of neceſſity the <hi>Malady</hi> quits the patient in the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant by the <hi>Criſis,</hi> or elſe by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, by little and little.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:121191:105"/>
               <head>Definition of the <hi>Criſis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Now <hi>Criſis</hi> is a ſuddain change of the diſeaſe either to health, or to death; which is done then, when nature ſeparates the ill hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours from the good, to the end, ſhe may force them out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Two ſorts of <hi>Criſis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And of this <hi>Criſis,</hi> there is two ſorts; the one perfect, and the other imperfect. The imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is that, by which the matter is not abſolutely forced out of the body, but is evacuated from the Noble parts to the Ignoble, and from the interiour parts to the exteriour.</p>
               <p>The other, is called perfect, whereby nature even as Miſtris and Lady governing the body, doth abſolutely and wholly reject
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:121191:105"/>
the matter out of the body, and this is done either by vomiting, or by flux of blood at the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrills, or by menſtrue, or by the Hemorrhoides or by ſweatings, as we have ſaid above.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A pritty ſimilitude of <hi>Avicen,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Criſis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Avicenna,</hi> had an excellent underſtanding of <hi>Criſis</hi> when he ſaith, that, <q>The <hi>Criſis</hi> is no other thing, but the ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of two perſons, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the one againſt the other in a civill caſe: for, ſaith he, even as in one civill proceeding there doth concurr four ſorts of perſons: that is to ſay, he which accuſeth, he who is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, the witneſſes, and the Judge: In like manner, do theſe four concurr alſo, in the <hi>Criſis,</hi> firſt the accuſer, who is
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:121191:106"/>
the power which governs the body, ſecondly the <hi>Malady,</hi> which is accuſed; and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the witneſſes are, the ſignes of that <hi>Malady,</hi> and the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian is the Judge.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And even as the civil Judge giving ſentence, the one of the parties continues ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and the other is joyfull; ſo in like manner in the <hi>Criſis,</hi> if the ſignes are bad, the Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an adjudgeth the patient to die; and then he and his kindred, continue ſorrowfull, but if the ſignes be good, ſignifying vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory of the powers over the <hi>Malady,</hi> the Phyſitian makes Judgment, and paſſes ſentence that the Patient ſhall recover, and thereby he and his kindred continue joyfull,</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="167" facs="tcp:121191:106"/>
               <head>The Common Criticall judgment, of no value.</head>
               <p>It is true, that the greateſt number of <hi>Chirurgions</hi> do paſſe Judgement, but it is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly of no value; and that by reaſon of their not being able to diſcern that which cauſeth the ſaid <hi>Criſis,</hi> or rather by reaſon of his not obſerving it; for if they did calculate well the Critricall daies, they would not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in predicting the events, and would in no wife fail to hit the Mark.</p>
               <p>You muſt take notice in this place, that they hold that the <hi>Salutary Criſis</hi> arives ordinarily the ſeventh, fourteenth, or twenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth day: wherefore it is that thoſe dayes are called Criticall dayes. They foreſee the future <hi>Criſis</hi> by the ſignes of Coction which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear,
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:121191:107"/>
the fourth, eleventh, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteenth daies which are called Indicative and Contemplative dayes; for according to <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> the fourth day is the Indice of the ſeventh, the eighth is the beginning of the other week; the eleventh alſo is remarkable, becauſe it is the fourth of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther week, &amp; yet the ſeventeenth is remarkable, becauſe it is the fourth after the fourteenth &amp; the ſeventh from the eleventh: ſome do not go to ſearch ſo many fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, but they hold ſimply that the <hi>Criſis</hi> doth uſe to conclude either the fourth day or the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, or elſe the ninth and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth and fourteenth daies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Common opinion concerning the <hi>Criſis,</hi> is fallacious:</head>
               <p>As much upon the one ſide as the other; the one party are as
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:121191:107"/>
good ſhooters in a Crosbow as the other, for it is moſt certain that the <hi>Criſis</hi> is either ſooner or latter, aſcribing theſe daies of deciſion to the effects of the Moon; And ſo the Aſtrologers aſſigne the Indices of <hi>Maladies,</hi> when the Moon is diſtant in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees about the fourth part, or about half of the <hi>Zodiac,</hi> from the true place where ſhe was at the beginning of the <hi>Maladie.</hi> But (becauſe her motion is more quick or ſlow at ſometimes then at others, &amp; ſometimes ſhe arives more late, and ſometimes more early to ſuch aſpects) that if it happen that upon a Critical day, the Moon is in her houſe, or in her exaltation with <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> which are benevolent and healthfull Planets, that doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note, that the change will be good.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:121191:108"/>
               <head>A moſt true ſigne concerning the <hi>Criſis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And if the diſeaſe conſiſt in a great affluence of humours, it is good that the Moon be in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in a quartile aſpect, or in oppoſition. If the Moon be in the ſame time in Conjunction with the Sun or Saturn, it is an ill ſigne, and denotes that it will be a very dangerous diſeaſe, or elſe of a long continuance. If the Moon increaſing do accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>Saturn,</hi> preciſely in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the diſeaſe, it doth denote, that the <hi>Malady</hi> will be of a long Continuance, or Mortal. But if the diſeaſe happens then, when ſhe is in her decreaſe, it is a ſigne that the <hi>Malady</hi> will not continue long, and will not be dangerous: for this cauſe you ought not to ſleight the ſalubrious
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:121191:108"/>
or nocent ſignes of the Starrs, but to obſerve them exactly, to the end, that you may attain the honour of Prognoſticating Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely; for the wiſe man doth op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe himſelf to the mutation of the heavens made on the earth. And that no otherwiſe then in removing away, or repairing the earthly matter wherein the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens do operate; or elſe not find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſubject to act upon, his Action is turned in an Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Charity of the Anthour is Commendable.</head>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, I deſire in this place to make known that the fall of an Innumerable multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of men, is occaſioned by not knowing any thing but the name and word onely of <hi>Criſis,</hi> and not the cauſe of the effect.
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:121191:109"/>
And that ſeverall men who by by their extream ignorance, cauſe the Heaven and the Earth to be opened, and fix there their eares, and do there bound the eyes of their underſtanding, to the end, that they may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the earth, covering or Entombing their errours, which ought rather to ſerve as Scarlet, to make them bluſh. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the manner how!</p>
               <p>It is certain that our bodies are moved, and inflamed by the ſuperiour bodies, otherwiſe they could not ſuffer; for in the method of the diſtribution of things, the body of the Moon in her Sphere doth by the points of the <hi>Zodiac</hi> produce that mutation which is made from time to time, in all bodies, none excepted. As for example.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:121191:109"/>
               <head>Example concerning the above named opinion.</head>
               <p>If it happen that ſome one is taken ſick, the Moon being in the firſt point of <hi>Aries,</hi> infallibly, on the fourth day following, counting from the time of fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſick, the Moon is found in a point repugnant in property to that wherein ſhe was at the time of the firſt falling ſick; And then is the <hi>Criſis</hi> made either by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting flux of blood, flux of the belly, or ſweatings, as we have ſaid before. In this day is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited the offering force to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whether it be by blooding or Phyſick, either ſolutive or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringent, for fear that nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to diſcharge her ſelf by ſweat, be not forced to do it by other Emunctory; and for this cauſe evacuation is to be practiſed
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:121191:110"/>
upon the third or fifth day from the beginning of the ſickneſſe. And none can deny, (however he be opinionate of himſelf) but that this is true.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A too Common errour.</head>
               <p>But alas, behold the evil which doth often (nay moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly) happen, That while men are attending the <hi>Criſis</hi> on the fourth day, becauſe of the above mentioned motion of the Moon, it happens that the Moon expedites her courſe, and comes on the third day to the point which cauſeth the <hi>Criſis.</hi> And without taking notice thereof the Phyſician who would count her hours, makes too much haſte, and onely counts the fourth day for the <hi>Criſis,</hi> and without any other Ceremony, being bold, cauſeth the ſick perſon to be
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:121191:110"/>
blooded or purged, and by that meanes ſends him to ask St. <hi>Peter</hi> for his Keys to open heaven with.</p>
               <p>And when the Moon becomes declining or Retrograde, ſhe is not come to that point untill the fifth day, wherein happens the ſame overſight. Behold the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why <hi>Hippocrates. Lib. de fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus.</hi> would have the Phyſitian to have but a few patients, and to languiſh with them for whom, as ſaith <hi>Paracelſus,</hi> he is created father, and not Doctor.</p>
               <p>I ſhould enlarge my ſelf fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon this diſcourſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter, to make ſeen to the eye, and felt (by the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) the great errour which is commonly committed in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon Criticall daies, and ſhould ſhew the true meanes of giving a true Judgement accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſecond cauſes, of either
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:121191:111"/>
life or death. But becauſe that doth require a greater ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that the age of a man will not ſuffice for it; I ſhall ſo bear, praying to God that he will be pleaſed ſo to bleſſe our Labours, that what we do, may be to his honour and glory, the edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and benefit of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the ſafety and ſalvation of our own ſouls. To whom Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son, and holy Spirit, be honour and glory eternally, Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:111"/>
            <head>To the Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Reader. <hi>A Quadrine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Beleeve not, That, In Oſtentation, I have writ this Treatiſe of <hi>Pleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as a friend to life, I undertook to ſhew its operation, In this Book.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:121191:112"/>
            <head>A <hi>TABLE</hi> OF THE Chapters.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. I.</label>
               <item>WHat <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> is, Its properties, and that which muſt be particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved for the good performance thereof.</item>
               <label>CHAP. II.</label>
               <item>How that the <hi>Chirurgion</hi> ought not to be ignorant of Aſtrology, and of the profit that comes thereby, as well for <hi>Phlebotomy,</hi> as for all
<pb facs="tcp:121191:112"/>
the <hi>Maladies</hi> which do happen unto humane bodies. The Sympathy of the Starrs therewith, and other diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veryes moſt uſefull for a <hi>Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>CHAP. III.</label>
               <item>Of the time of Neceſſity, wherein are ſhewn the <hi>Maladies,</hi> wherein <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> doth neceſſarily fall out.</item>
               <label>CHAP. IV.</label>
               <item>Of the time of Election, for the Inferiour Root, and of the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Root, which extends its ſelf to to the knowledge of the Starrs, as well in the Concurrence which they have to the parts of our bodies, as upon the Humours and <hi>Maladies</hi> which happen therein.</item>
               <label>CHAP. V.</label>
               <item>That it is neceſſary that a <hi>Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> have the Aſtronomicall figure in his ſtudy, or at leaſt in his ſhop, and of the benefit that proceeds therefrom, as well to the Patients
<pb facs="tcp:121191:113"/>
as thoſe that exerciſe or practice it, which is proved by a Hiſtory, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examples. Alſo that it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to mundify the blood, than to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuate it; with the diſcovery of two excellent remedies for that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</item>
               <label>CHAP. VI.</label>
               <item>Of the Veins proper to be blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for ſeveral infirmities, which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to humane bodies; together with the benefit and the manner of uſing of Cupping-glaſſes, with Scarrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and without it; and of that which is to be obſerved in this ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; and laſtly of <hi>Horſe-leech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es.</hi>
               </item>
               <label> </label>
               <item>A ſhort treatiſe or diſcourſe of <hi>Criſis</hi>'s, wherein is demonſtrated how men do deceive themſelves in the judgement of them, not knowing the motion of the Starrs.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
